Test test is that coming through on there? Well, but it's clear
I'll now call to order this meeting of committees of Lancaster City Council for October 6 20 25 Mr. Harris, would you please begin with the roll call of members? Yes, madam president
Mr. Mann here. Mr. Roya here. Mr. Cleese. Yeah, miss Craig Ms. Diaz?
Here.
Mr. Hirsch? Here. And President Peke?
Here. Councilor Craig is excused this evening. A few reminders and announcements at the top of the meeting. I first ask that you please silence your phones and devices if you haven't done so already. This meeting and its participants are being recorded. Thank you for bearing with us as we work through some new audio challenges with a new system. There will be some growing pains, and thank you for adapting with us. one of those is that we are taking this committee meeting from the dais just because we're still working on the wireless microphones so that's why we're up here this evening and not at our table tonight again we have meetings of committees of council there's no general public comment period during these meetings however committee chairs will call for comments from the public for legislative items that's bills and resolutions comments are limited to three minutes per speaker and you must begin with your name and your block of residents for our meeting record to keep time during those comments i will use my light it will be green when a speaker begins it will blink yellow when there is a minute remaining and then blink red when three minutes has been exhausted counselors will move to the approval of our september 2nd 2025 committee meeting minutes motion to approve second again we have a motion and a second counselors any comments on the minutes hearing none mr harris mr mann aye
Aye. Mr. Arroyo? Aye. Mr. Cleese? Aye. Ms. Diaz? Aye. Mr. Hirsch?
Aye. And President Becker? Aye. That will take us to the Personnel Committee meeting. Turning it over to Councilor Calixto.
Thank you, Madam President. The Personnel Committee has four items on the agenda for tonight. The first item is the nomination of Theodore Griffiths for appointment to the Planning Commission. minister griffiths was expected to attend the meeting tonight but unfortunately for enforcing circumstances he cannot attend the meeting tonight in order to tell us his thoughts about his nomination so we expect him to attend the next meeting on october 14th and so we move on to the second item which is the nomination of heidi shirk for reappointment to the planning commission miss shirk currently serves on the board for um but her term has expired so she's willing to be reappointed to continue to serve on the board with that i'll open up for comments or questions for from the committee and members of council hearing none any questions or comments from the public so thank you so we i'll make a motion to move this nomination to our next council meeting on october 14th second all in favors aye the next item is the nomination of uh heidi shirk no no denomination of uh iber guerrero lopez for the appointment to the lincaster industrial development authority and um miss guerrero lopez current term has expired on the board and she's willing to be reappointed and i'll open up four questions and comments from members of the committee and from council from the public i'll make a motion to move this nomination to our next council meeting on october 14th second all in favors aye and the last item is the nomination of darcy polak for reappointment to the lancaster county convention center authority and mr pollock has been serving on the board for quite some time and his term has expired and he has expressed his interest in being reappointed i'll open up FOR QUESTIONS OR COMMENTS FROM MEMBERS OF THE COMMITTEE AND FROM COUNCIL. FROM THE PUBLIC, I'LL MAKE A MOTION TO MOVE THIS NOMINATION TO OUR FULL COUNCIL MEETING ON OCTOBER 14th.
SECOND.
ALL IN FAVORS? AYE. SO THAT CONCLUDES THE PERSONAL COMMITTEE, MADAM PRESIDENT.
CHAIR KALEKS, I DON'T BELIEVE WE MADE A MOTION ON THEODORE GRIFFITH'S NOMINATION, AND I FEEL that we should uh motion to move uh his nomination to our october 14th meeting okay so i'll make a
motion to move this nomination to the next council meeting on october 14th then the second all in favor aye so that concludes the personal committee madam president thank you very much counselor
colleagues uh we will look forward to seeing mr griffiths we have met him uh previously during our ethics commission process we'll look forward to seeing him seeing him in person at the next meeting uh next we will move to the finance committee council arroyo thank you council
president we have two items on the agenda for this evening's finance committee uh administration bill number 11 and administration bill number 12. i would invite director campbell who will be giving a budget overview presentation on the 2026 budget good evening director campbell sometimes it just
takes like a second a little bit of that cool is that we got we'll go with that i was are they both uh plugged in at the same time and is that okay again we're still learning a brand new system
they're um working on that maybe i can just give the overview oh there we go perfect great um so we will be talking about both of these bills together they they coincide um with each other um both the budget and the the real estate tax rates um so first of all thank you all for taking time to review the 2026 proposed budget this evening um i'm remembering that when we were that at this time last year we were presenting you with two different budgets um i'm grateful we don't have to produce two budgets this year this has definitely made the comp the budget process less complicated um though as many of you who who have created budgets know there's still a lot of OF WORK INVOLVED SO GIVEN THAT BEFORE I DIVE INTO THE BUDGET ITSELF I JUST WANTED TO GIVE A BIG THANK YOU TO OUR ACCOUNTING TEAM WHO SPENT A LOT OF HOURS ON THIS AND ACTUALLY ARE CURRENTLY UPSTAIRS WORKING ON ON ENSURING THAT THE BUDGET BOOKLET IS IS WORKING RIGHT SO IT'S DEFINITELY A COLLECTIVE EFFORT AND WE CAN'T DO THIS WITH JUST ONE PERSON OR EVEN JUST ONE TEAM THOUGH SO JUST A BIG THANKS TO ALL INVOLVED SO TONIGHT BEGINS THE THE PUBLIC input portion of the 2026 budget process we will have a draft of the budget posted on the website tomorrow morning and it will be available on engage lancaster as well to make comments on i want to emphasize again that this is a draft so nothing is set in stone there's a number of opportunities for everyone to interact with this budget before it is adopted i have a schedule included at the end of my presentation that we will go over to talk about all of the dates and options so let's jump in tonight as we have had have as we've done traditionally I'm going to give a very high level overview of the budget the budget hearings coming up later this month and in November we'll provide many more details from the departments and the various funds on both the expenses and the revenue in the budget the biggest noteworthy subject the mayor talked ABOUT THIS IN HER ADDRESS WE ARE NOT PROPOSING ANY INCREASES IN TAXES OR FEES FOR CITY RESIDENTS THIS YEAR THIS MEANS NO REAL ESTATE OR EARNED INCOME TAX FEE TAX INCREASE AND NO INCREASES IN UTILITY FEES FOR INSIDE CITY CUSTOMERS WE DID SUBMIT A WATER RATE CASE WATER RATE INCREASE CASE TO THE PUC LAST WEEK SO WE DO ANTICIPATE AN INCREASE IN WATER RATES FOR CUSTOMERS OUTSIDE of the city at some point in 2026 it's very unlikely that we will receive approval for the full increase that we requested the puc doesn't typically do that so we do not know yet what this increase will be nor do we know when it will take place the puc has to process it first so a few other highlights for the general fund arpa funding has now ended this means a reduction in income from 2025 of 2.4 million earned income tax is coming in almost exactly as we projected with the increased rates this year we're anticipating that this will continue to grow with the natural increases in income we continue to hear that lancaster county and city incomes are continuing to increase and so we will keep watching that based on national trends as well this next point feels like a broken record but as is the case every year medical costs are rising as well as pensions the vast majority of our salaries are set by collective bargaining agreements and so those push costs up as well there are ten and a half positions that are included in this year's general fund budget that were vacant previously or are new the mayor noted the return of the chief of staff position in her address on September 23rd other positions are either revenue neutral related to permitting and building code functions or long overdue especially those in hr and we will be discussing each of those as we move through the budget the department overviews at the budget hearings on october 21st and november 18th and then the enterprise funds so the water sewer storm water and the solid waste and recycling fund those four will be discussed in much greater detail on november 18th so i will not get into those this evening other than i mentioned earlier that we're not planning to increase fees within the CITY. THIS SLIDE SHOWS THE TOTAL OF THE OPERATING EXPENSES FOR ALL OF THE CITY FUNDS. THIS INCLUDES BOTH THE GENERAL FUND, WHICH IS GENERAL OPERATIONS OF THE CITY, AND THE FOUR ENTERPRISE FUNDS THAT I JUST MENTIONED, WATER FUNDS, SEWER FUND, SOLID WASTE AND RECYCLING AND THE STORM WATER MANAGEMENT FUND. THIS TOTAL IS 159.6 MILLION, SO ABOUT 160 MILLION FOR ALL FUNDS COMBINED. THIS IS ONLY ABOUT A 1% TOTAL increase from last year you can see that about 52 of the total budget is the general fund and so because the general fund is such a large portion of that budget i'm going to spend the rest of the presentation focused on that and again as i just mentioned the enterprise funds will be addressed in more detail on on november 18th so for the general fund this graph shows the breakdown of our revenue in the regular budget you're in the budget we don't have to worry about REGULAR HOME RULE BUDGET ANYMORE. THE LARGEST PORTION OF THE FUNDS COME FROM PROPERTY TAXES, BUT THAT'S STILL JUST 42% OF THE BUDGET, SO IT'S LESS THAN HALF OF THE FULL BUDGET. SO THE OTHER SOURCES OF REVENUE INCLUDE EARNED INCOME, WHICH IS ABOUT 21% OF THE REVENUE. I WILL HAVE A SLIDE ON THAT A LITTLE BIT LATER. REAL ESTATE TRANSFER TAX AND LOCAL SERVICES TAX, THESE TAXES COMBINED ARE NOT A LOT OF a lot of revenue it's only about four percent of the total um and i'll share a little bit more details on the real estate transfer tax in a minute as well um other revenue categories the city charges fees for some of the services as well as fines and those do bring in revenue for the city between all the fees and and for services and fines this totals about 17 of our regular budget revenue and these services include things like building permits plumbing licenses zoning permits health licenses right-of-way permit fees parking violations and public safety related activities the other revenue category on here which is the third one on the list and that's about 11 of the regular budget this includes a multitude of revenue sources including payments from the enterprise funds for services that the general fund provides and also grant funds that have been awarded to help with specific projects and finally as the mayor mentioned in her speech on September 23rd we are using cash reserves of one million which is about one percent of the budget this will still keep us at approximately 20 percent in our cash reserve fund which is in line with our proposed cash reserve policy that is currently being considered within the home rule administrative code and this THIS USE OF RESERVE FUNDS HELPS US TO SMOOTH THE ARPA CLIFF. JUST BRIEFLY, BEFORE WE LOOK AT EXPENSES, WELL, BEFORE WE LOOK AT EXPENSES, BECAUSE WE'RE NOT GOING TO SPEND A LOT OF TIME ON REVENUE DURING THE BUDGET HEARINGS THAT ARE COMING UP LATER, I DID WANT TO SPEND A COUPLE MINUTES ON A COUPLE OF THE REVENUE CATEGORIES. SO WE AREN'T PROPOSING INCREASING REAL ESTATE TAXES THIS YEAR, BUT I STILL LIKE TO SHOW THIS like to show this chart each year this is the total assessed value of real estate within the city and this helps helps us to determine the millage rate of the real estate tax so this chart you can see shows that there's very little change in property assessments in the city from year to year except in 2018 when the county implemented a reassessment since that time the city's overall tax base has grown only three percent and you can see that about a third of the property is tax exempt and cannot be cannot be taxed so we don't really see this number move a whole lot i will say too that the county is planning a tax reassessment in 2027 this is the first one since 2018 however with those reassessments we do need to lower the tax millage rate to be revenue neutral so we're not projecting any significant increases in real estate tax revenue over the next years all right the real estate transfer tax this is the tax that happens when a property is sold so the city splits this tax with the school district and this along with the earned income tax often is a pretty good indicator of whether or not the economy is healthy so the real estate tax tends to increase ever so slightly or stay the same in a healthy real estate market and you can see that playing out generally there's a few years in here with some anomalies that you can see so i'll just mention those in 2018 that's getting towards the beginning of this chart now park city was actually sold so that contributed to almost half the taxes in this category for that year 21 and 22 as we all know were periods of low mortgage interest rates and a high push for property sales and transfers that was at a national level so we saw that playing out here too and then this year 2025 we did see a jump because of the real estate selling for the data center which pushed us over what we had budgeted but we accounted for that anomaly in the budget for 2026 we're not anticipating that again and so we've kept the budget the same as 2025. all right on to earned income tax so as you know we increased the rate for our earned income tax last year year. We spent quite a bit of time reviewing the impacts of this on the 2025 budget last year. Based on the research and the advice that we received, we included what I'll describe as a lag for when the increase would actually start. So though the increase actually started January 1st, we didn't assume in the budget that we would actually see the increase fully take effect until after the first quarter of the year. And as we have analyzed the income through the end of august this year our budget appears to be on on track for the actual income we are receiving so that appears to be a good projection for the year so in addition to the to the tax increase from last year we continue to see a slight rise in income levels which contributes to a natural increase in earned income tax income for the city um so over the past 10 YEARS, THAT HAS AVERAGED ABOUT 5%, GIVE OR TAKE. AND WE'RE CONTINUING TO SEE THAT TREND. WE'RE WATCHING THE ECONOMY PRETTY CLOSELY, BUT WE THINK THIS WILL CONTINUE INTO 2026. SO IF YOU LOOK AT THIS GRAPH CLOSELY, IF YOU LIKE TO CRUNCH NUMBERS, YOU WILL SEE THAT 2026 JUMPS MORE THAN 5% FROM 2025. AND THIS IS BECAUSE WE ARE INCLUDING A FULL YEAR OF RECEIVING THE EARNED INCOME TAX AT THE CURRENT LEVEL NOW, AS WELL AS THE NATURAL INCOME INCREASE PROJECTIONS. SO I JUST WANTED TO SAY THAT ALL TO MAKE IT CLEAR THAT WE'RE NOT PROJECTING AN INCREASE IN THE TAX RATES. WE'RE SIMPLY PROJECTING THAT INCOME INCREASE BECAUSE OF THOSE FACTORS. ALL RIGHT. SO NOW WE'RE GOING TO LOOK AT A LITTLE BIT OF EXPENSES. WE HAVE A COUPLE OF DIFFERENT GRAPHS TO SHOW THE EXPENSES FOR THE GENERAL FUND TONIGHT, AND I WANTED TO JUST START WITH THIS ONE. WE INCLUDED THIS ONE FOR THE FIRST TIME LAST YEAR, AND I I THINK IT GIVES A PRETTY GOOD IDEA OF THE BREAKDOWNS. SO AS YOU LOOK AT THE BREAKDOWNS OF THE GENERAL FUND EXPENSES, OUR BIGGEST EXPENSE CATEGORIES ARE IN PUBLIC SAFETY. THIS IS ALWAYS THE CASE. IT'S A TOTAL OF ABOUT 54% OF OUR BUDGET THAT GOES TO FIRE AND POLICE. THESE ARE SHOWN ON THE BOTTOM BAR IN RED FOR POLICE AND THE DARK GRAY FOR FIRE. AND LAST YEAR, IF YOU REMEMBER THE MANY DISCUSSIONS ABOUT EARNED INCOME TAX IN OUR HOME CONVERSATIONS, WE SHOWED YOU THAT PROPERTY TAX AND EARNED INCOME TAX ARE TWO HIGHEST INCOME OR REVENUE BASES ONLY COVERED THE POLICE AND FIRE EXPENSES FOR THE CITY WHILE ALL OF THOSE SERVICES REQUIRED COVERAGE FROM ELSEWHERE. THIS CHART SHOWS THAT THIS IS STARTING TO CHANGE FOR THE FIRST TIME THANKS TO THE EARNED INCOME TAX INCREASE. SO PROPERTY TAX AND EARNED INCOME TAX BECAUSE OF THIS of this increase now make up about 63 percent of the revenue budget while this doesn't nearly cover all of our services it's a huge help as we have reached that cliff for arpa in 2025 that i was talking about and are needing to increase support for some of the other services without arpa funding and then this is just a different version of looking at the expenses for the general fund after public safety the next largest category of general expenses is the category that we are now describing as supporting expenses this holds pension medical and debt expenses so it's about 15 percent of the total budget this category also includes just a very small amount of funding for organizations like the library lancaster rec and lemsa but that amounts to about less than five percent of the total expenses for this category so of that 15 percent and then the other categories YOU CAN SEE HERE OF THE BUDGET INCLUDE THE REMAINING DEPARTMENTS. SO C-PED, THE COMMUNITY PLANNING AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT IS AT 7%, ADMINISTRATIVE SERVICES IS AT 10%, PUBLIC WORKS IS AT 12%, AND NEIGHBORHOOD ENGAGEMENT COMES IN JUST UNDER 2% OF THE FULL BUDGET. THE OTHER TWO VERY TINY PORTIONS TOTALING JUST OVER 1% OF THE BUDGET TOGETHER INCLUDE THE MAYOR AND SOLICITORS OFFICE AND THE ELECTED WORK. SO CITY COUNCIL, CITY CLERK, AND THE CONTROLLER EXPENSES. THIS IS ANOTHER SLIDE THAT WE created last year and I thought it might be helpful to see again this shows the difference in costs in in our four categories of expenses in the general fund so the largest increase in cost this year is in salaries this is due to adding positions that I mentioned in the opening slide as well as finally budgeting for a fully staffed police bureau we haven't done this for a number of years but thanks to some good recruiting efforts this year we're feeling confident that we're going to be close to fully staffed next year the next three sides i will move through fairly quickly but they show a bit more detail about the supporting services so medical pension and debt these are as i've been saying very large drivers of cost increases for us so i just wanted to show these briefly this is the medical expenses for the city this is showing all funds so it does include enterprise funds in this budget as well year-over-year medical costs have increased an average of 4.5 percent since 2016. saw some bigger jumps in 2021 and 2022 after covid but then some leveling out in 2023 jumped again in 2024 and some slighter lower increases in 25 and 26. we are self-insured so these numbers are results of much analysis but they are also still projections we watch these numbers pretty closely to ensure that they're staying in line with what we have projected and additionally I will say the fact that we're self-insured has helped to keep these costs down they're not rising as much as other organizations are seeing however we are still embarking on a pretty big project reviewing these costs in 2026 which we're hopeful will have positive results on costs in 2027 and beyond while still ensuring that we're providing a top level of health care benefits to our EMPLOYEES SO I WILL BE TALKING MORE ABOUT THAT ON OCTOBER 21ST IN MY ADMIN SERVICES PRESENTATION AS WELL THIS SLIDE SHOWS THE COMPARISON OF THE PENSION COST OBLIGATIONS FOR THE CITY VERSUS THE STATE PENSION AID THAT WE RECEIVE SO AS YOU CAN SEE THERE'S A STEADY INCREASE FOR THE THREE COMBINED PENSIONS THE POLICE FIRE AND NON-UNIFORMED THE NU UP THERE THOSE ARE THE RED BLACK AND and gray or blue, I'm not sure what that color is. And then the state pension aid is the yellow bar. So you can see that that has increased at a much lower rate. Our obligations have risen by $4.8 million in the last 10 years, while state aid has only increased by $1.9 million during the same period. I don't think I showed this slide last year, so I wanted to pull this out again. This is the general fund debt service. as you can see debt did jump in 2024 because of the 2022 bond payments some of the larger projects in that bond were the creation of the parks master plan the police department had some window replacements and other renovations that were partially covered by a grant but we needed some capital funding as well and then some of the costs of the welcome center renovations that weren't funded by the grants we needed as well it also included much of the bike lane work that's been COMPLETED THROUGHOUT THE CITY, AGAIN, IN CONJUNCTION WITH SOME GRANTS FOR THAT WORK. I DID WANT TO NOTE JUST ONE THING THAT'S NOT ON THIS SLIDE THAT'S RELEVANT TO THIS SLIDE. IN THE NEXT SLIDE, YOU'LL SEE AN INCREASE IN 2027 FOR DEBT SERVICE, AS I SHOW THESE 10-YEAR PROJECTIONS. THIS JUMP ACCOUNTS FOR THE 2025 BOND PAYMENTS STARTING, THE ONES THAT WERE APPROVED THIS YEAR. THESE PROJECTS HAVE BEEN INCLUDED IN THE CAPITAL PLAN THAT WAS APPROVED A COUPLE OF WEEKS AGO AND SOME OF THOSE MAJOR PROJECTS AGAIN JUST INCLUDE THE WORK TO IMPLEMENT A NEW THAT IMPLEMENT THE NEW MASTER PARKS PLAN SOME OF THE WORK OF IMPLEMENTING VISION ZERO RENOVATIONS NEEDED FOR THE OPERATION CENTER AND OTHER THINGS THAT YOU HAVE SEEN IN THAT CAPITAL PLAN AND BECAUSE WE NOW HAVE A CAPITAL PLAN WE'LL BE REPORTING ON THESE PROJECTIONS MUCH MORE REGULARLY QUARTERLY ACTUALLY AND YOU'LL SEE THE CAPITAL BUDGET DEBT SURFACING PROJECTIONS START to show up in the operating expense projections all right and as a final slide regarding the numbers I want to show the projections over the next 10 years so this is this is very much projections it's 10 years so it's it's hard to say that this is this is not set in stone by any means but this is at this time assuming no additional tax increases so this is not including any sort of real estate or earned income tax increases again these are very much projections I wanted to point out that even with increased debt payments for the 2025 bond which were not included in the projections from last year that we were working on our fund balance which is the cash reserve the bottom line there remains at 15% through 2029 while increasing other expenses based on on salary increases medical pension etc so our goal is to keep and you'll see this in the policy is to keep the cash reserve between 15 and 20 percent ideally on the higher end of that so this means that we will have some work to do in the next few years to continue to try to keep the expenses down but it also isn't unreachable unreachable to remove these deficits in the upcoming years we won't necessarily need to increase taxes to remove those deficits um the projection if you recall looked much bleaker last year when we were showing what would happen without an earned income tax increase in 2025. so i'm still feeling very positive um that we can continue to work to eliminate some of these deficits through some of the efficiencies that we're building now and to ensure that we're continuing to provide you know necessary services without continuing to increase taxes and finally before i stop for questions i did want to ensure THAT YOU HAVE THE FULL BUDGET SCHEDULE FOR ANY SORT OF INPUT SO FROM COUNCIL OR FROM THE PUBLIC WE HAD A DIFFERENT BUDGET PROCESS LAST YEAR BECAUSE WE WERE VOTING ON HOME RULE AND WE HAVE A DIFFERENT BUDGET PROCESS THIS YEAR BECAUSE THE HOME RULE CHARTER IS NOW IN EFFECT SO WE WILL POST THE DRAFT OF THE BUDGET ONLINE TOMORROW AND IT WILL BE AVAILABLE FOR REVIEW starting tomorrow through the time of adoption budget questions and comments can be posted on Engage Lancaster anytime before December 1st and we will respond to them on it on Engage Lancaster and we will also respond at one of the various meetings listed here as as we get them so as they come in and instead of having a full Saturday budget hearing this year as we've done in the past we're dividing that into two evenings as i've been mentioning so the first one is on october 21st and that'll include details from the departments that you see here administrative services cped fire and police the second will be held on november 18th with the list included here for that date so the mayor's office solicitor's office and elected officials neighborhood engagement public works and then the utility funds are all of the enterprise funds and again i'll answer any questions that come through the engagement the engaged Lancaster platform at both of those sessions then the first reading of the budget ordinance and the and the real estate tax ordinance will be November 25th with the second following at the next regular council meeting which is December 9th and in between those I'm available to answer any final questions at the finance committee meeting on Monday and I will stop there great thank you director Campbell
for the presentation and uh appreciate you and your team's hard work as mayor sirachi mentioned in a previous meeting this is the earliest we've ever had a budget presentation so very grateful for the hard work i'll open it up to the finance committee for any questions or comments full
counsel counselor thank you uh thank you director campbell for um the detailed presentation and look forward to getting into these numbers a little further i have a very um brief question which JUST WHAT IS THE STATUS OF THE FINANCIAL STATEMENT AUDIT FOR 2024? YEAH, IT'S TAKING LONGER THAN
WE EXPECTED, BUT WE EXPECT IT TO BE DONE BY THE END OF OCTOBER.
WONDERFUL. THANK YOU.
COUNSELOR OMID? THANK YOU, MR. VICE PRESIDENT. AND THANK YOU, DIRECTOR CAMPBELL, FOR THE PRESENTATION. I JUST HAD TWO QUESTIONS. FIRST, WITH THE PROJECTIONS WITH SOME UPCOMING DEFICITS AND SOME UPCOMING DEPLETIONS OF FUND BALANCES, WHAT ARE SOME WAYS THAT THE ADMINISTRATION IS going to be keeping the increase in expenses year over year down um to avoid a tax increase
yeah it's a great question um so a couple of the things that we're looking at one is um what i what i mentioned which is around the health care costs that's always a huge driver for us and so i will be talking more about it on october 21st so i'm going to say come back then to hear more about it but we are embarking on a pretty big project for that and the other pieces that we have been including some new technology which costs some upfront but we're hoping that that also helps us to improve
efficiencies down the road thank you my final question was regarding the earned income tax I know there was a previous discussion about an exemption and what that would look like and the option for council to have maybe a different a DIFFERENT WAY WE COULD ALLOT THOSE FUNDS TOWARDS A PROGRAM THAT BENEFITS LOW INCOME RESIDENTS. IS THERE ANY UPDATE ON THAT OR SHOULD WE SUSPECT THAT IN THE NEXT MEETING AS WELL? I WOULD LOOK TO COUNCIL TO
GIVE SOME SUGGESTIONS FOR THAT, BUT I THINK WE'RE OPEN TO LOOKING AT THAT IN THE BUDGET. AND I THINK THAT THERE ARE
SOME OTHER OPPORTUNITIES FOR FUNDING THE CRITICAL REPAIR PROGRAM THAT COUNCIL HAS EXPRESSED INTEREST IN. WE ARE HAVING SOME INTERNAL CONVERSATIONS ABOUT THE what that amount might need to look like in order to sustain the program year over year and we'll be coming back to council um with further information uh in the i can't i not exactly sure what meeting but sometime in november or december thank you so this current budget as
presented does not account for those lost revenues the lost revenues if there was an exemption i'm
like no because that um i believe at the presentation that we had it was demonstrated that the um the effectively that it would cost more to administer than the benefit would provide for and so no there is no um this budget does not comp contemplate any reduction in earned income tax revenues as it relates to that exemption however we do not want to drop the thread of the conversation related to the critical repair program and as you know we have allocated some arpa funds into that and that has really bolstered that program over time and i think that there's continued interest from council is what i understand to seek additional funding for that particular program so we will be talking about that but outside of the budget thank you
and yeah that was my question the total dollars not as much of it whatever program it may be but the total dollars being recognized in the budget yes thank you thank you that concludes my questions
thank you and thank you director campbell thank you councilman and just add to that i have had conversations with director campbell around uh coming back to council before the end of the year to uh discuss the tax exemption again so in a future date we'll have another presentation regarding the logistics of a tax exemption and some potentially other ideas as director campbell mentioned this is this budget is not final there are still opportunities to to make some changes so look forward to hearing some some of those ideas as we move forward
council president thank you director campbell uh the 10-year projection page so we've seen this again and again again and this year we have the revenue also includes greater earned income tax so in the past these projections have always assumed that we did there's no change so uh real estate or property taxes were flat i'm assuming that also means that these projections mean that the earned income tax is flat so it doesn't change or does this assume the five percent growth or does it assume essentially no growth from here um it assumes
i believe this is a three percent growth we didn't want to put five percent in but it does
assume a slight growth so like a conservative amount of growth but not necessarily what we've seen for that category correct well or that we believe we'll see for that category as i was
mentioning last year it compounds a little bit because we have increased the fee sure or the that tax rate this year um so it's gonna it's gonna show a higher got it in the budget thank
you for helping me understand that thank you council president any additional questions or COMMENTS FROM COUNCIL GREAT AT THIS TIME PRIOR TO CALLING FOR A MOTION ON THE BILLS I'LL OPEN THE FLOOR FOR PUBLIC COMMENT AS IT RELATES TO BILL NUMBER 11 OR BILL NUMBER 12. ANY PUBLIC COMMENT
YOU MAY JUST NEED TO TURN THAT ON GREAT THANK YOU HELLO TONY DASTRO 700 BLOCK OF NEW HOLLAND AVENUE UM FIRST I WANT TO THANK YOU COUNCILOR IMED FOR MENTIONING THE TAX EXEMPTION UH AND I THINK THAT THE CITY NEEDS TO FOCUS ON GIVING THAT RELIEF DIRECTLY TO the residents of the city not circling it through another program i understand that there is some expense in the administrative cost to administer such a program but we're talking about three hundred thousand dollars of the fifteen point some million dollars the city gets in revenue total so it's less than two percent of the current revenue that we're receiving from income tax and then on top of the general operating fund budget it's pennies on the dollar so our poorest residents deserve that direct relief and i want to thank you for continuing to speak on that and then just for the record because it's a touches on some subject of later tonight the police is the largest part of our budget the pension is the largest part of the pensions management we have to do in the long term and so I hope we can look forward to more efforts concerted by the government to integrate the trust in our community into the police department thank you thank you
MR. DOSTER, ANY ADDITIONAL PUBLIC COMMENT?
GOOD EVENING.
YOU MIGHT HAVE TO TURN IT ON THERE.
ALL RIGHT. JESSICA LOPEZ, LANCASTER CITY RESIDENT. MY QUESTION ISN'T FOR NOW, BUT LATER ON DOWN THE LINE, WHEN WE START TO INCREASE OUR TAXES AND START TO HIT PEOPLE, WE'RE NOT DOING IT THIS YEAR, BUT AS THE BUDGET CHANGES, IT'S GOING TO AFFECT PEOPLE WHO MAKE LESS MORE THAN IT WILL AFFECT PEOPLE WHO MAKE MORE IN THE CITY. So the question is, are we going to later on decide to decrease our police budget and protect the actual residents of the city? Are we going to cut community engagement and housing programs instead of cutting our police budget when our wage just won't be increased later on and it doesn't balance out appropriately?
Happy to try to answer that, Director Campbell. yeah um so the projections that were shown there were just projections assuming that expenses steadily increase um every year council is tasked with passing the budget so we will go through this process every year and have to either make tough decisions if needed to cut expenses or based on revenues maybe not have to cut expenses and that's understandable but the question is
is the council actually going to make those tough decisions and cut the police budget instead of CUTTING THE SERVICES THAT HELP OUR COMMUNITY.
THAT WOULD BE DEPENDING ON THAT COUNCIL.
JUST TO SPEAK TO THAT QUESTION, I WILL SAY THAT WE HAVE DONE A STAFFING STUDY FOR THE POLICE AND HAVE DECREASED THE NUMBER OF OFFICERS THAT WE HAVE BUDGETED FOR BY A PRETTY SIGNIFICANT AMOUNT THIS YEAR. SO I WILL SAY THAT WE HAVE TAKEN THOSE STEPS TO MAKE SURE WE ARE RIGHT SIZED, AND I THINK THAT DEMONSTRATES THE CITY'S COMMITMENT TO MAKING SURE WE ARE DOING THAT CONTINUALLY IN THE FUTURE. So whatever right size may mean we we have looked at that and I would hope that future councils and administrations would continue to do
That thank you any additional public comment
You might need a slide that back and it's okay to leave that on thank you
Should be good. Yep. Thank you So you you said that you've done the the work to justify the size of the police department? is that data publicly available or can it be made publicly available to show the justification for
the size of i believe i believe that the staffing study information is lives on somewhere on the city website it's certainly documented in the meetings that we had um that we discussed it but i can't say for certain exactly where that is today besides those meetings
i would just say that i would echo that to see that disproportionate amount of the budget dedicated to police when we have 2%, I believe it was, for community engagement, 12% for public works. We can all look around our city and I think we can all agree that it needs more than 12% of our budget in the infrastructure. I see idle police cars consistently. I see multiple police cars for basic traffic stops. And I have a hard time believing that those kinds of things were found in the justification for the size of our police department when we're committing only 12 percent to public works and two percent to public engagement
thank you any additional public comment great thank you director campbell with that uh with that i will motion to move bill number 11 2025 to the first reading for first reading ON NOVEMBER 25th WE HAVE A MOTION AND A SECOND ALL THOSE IN FAVOR AYE AYE SECOND OUR MOTION TO MOVE ADMINISTRATION BILL NUMBER 12 TO THE FOR FIRST READING ON NOVEMBER 25th WE HAVE A MOTION AND A SECOND ALL THOSE IN FAVOR AYE AYE THAT CONCLUDES THE FINANCE COMMITTEE COUNCIL PRESIDENT
THANK YOU VERY MUCH COUNCILOR ARROYO WE'LL NOW MOVE INTO OUR COMMUNITY PLANNING COMMITTEE
uh handing it over then to counselor craig hit it again no there you go okay great thank you
um we have five items on the agenda this evening first of them being um the review of the historical commission recommendation for an after-the-fact demolition and new construction at 444 west lemon street um is there someone here from the historical commission yes that'll be
THAT'S FINE.
GOOD EVENING, CHRISTOPHER PETERS, CHAIR OF THE HISTORICAL COMMISSION. WITH ME TONIGHT IS VICE CHAIR DANIELLE AND FORMER VICE CHAIR STEVE FUNK AS WELL. AS WAS MENTIONED, THERE WAS A PROPOSAL BROUGHT BEFORE US. IT WAS AFTER THE FACT DEMOLITION AND NEW CONSTRUCTION. THIS IS OVER ON LEMON STREET. WHAT OCCURRED, AND I TRUST MAYBE YOU'VE DRIVEN BY AND SEEN IT, THERE'S A STRETCH OF TWO-AND-A-HALF STORY ROW HOMES homes that have a dormer there's 13 in a row and in fact on that those couple blocks there's very there's some continuity there with 14 in a row and even more on that street so what happened is the gable roof was removed dormer was removed and a new basically third floor was constructed we did not see this until last month after it was constructed so we're recommending to the city council to deny certificate of appropriateness and we based it on uh secretary of interior standards two five and nine if you don't mind i'll read just a couple quotes there uh the historic character of property shall be retained and preserved the removal of historic materials or alteration of features and spaces that characterize a property shall be avoided that's number two number five distinct features finishes construction techniques shall be preserved and number nine exterior regarding exterior alterations specifically shall not destroy historic historic materials that characterize the property the secretary of the interior standards actually has some recommendations when it comes to dormers and that's specifically what's going on with this application primarily one of their recommendations is historic dormers that are part of the original design should not be altered in scalar form so that dormer was removed the gable ROOF WAS REMOVED AND AN ENTIRE THIRD FLOOR WAS PUT IN ITS PLACE SO THERE'S A SERIES OF OTHER RECOMMENDATIONS BUT I CAN LEAVE IT AT THAT AND OPEN IT UP FOR QUESTIONS BUT THAT'S WHY WE RECOMMENDED DENIAL OF THIS APPLICATION ARE THERE ANY QUESTIONS FROM THE COMMITTEE
GO AHEAD HI COUNCIL GREG I BELIEVE WE ALSO HAVE THE GENTLEMAN THAT IS THE PROPERTY OWNER HERE ARE WE ABLE TO HEAR FROM THE PROPERTY OWNER AS WELL? ABSOLUTELY. THANK YOU, COUNCIL
GREG. MY NAME IS NATHAN CHARLES. I CURRENTLY LIVE ON 425 NORTH PRINCE STREET. I PREVIOUSLY LIVED ON 333 SOUTH PRINCE STREET AND I'M HOPING TO MOVE INTO 444 WEST LEMON. SO IT'S KIND OF A, I'M QUITE SURPRISED TO BE HERE. I THOUGHT WE WERE DOING you know doing everything right we have a permit so I was very surprised to you know essentially get after-the-fact notification kind of designation of this historic review so I have with me Jesse Pellman who is kind of the builder we've been working together on this this concept and idea for a very long time this is a fairly ambitious project i have been living in the city for many many years and periodically have gone through the exercise of i should buy a house and then i go look at the houses housing inventory and then it's like i should not buy a house i get very discouraged when i see bad flips and and you know properties that need a lot of renovation that i then compete with flippers for so this was the first opportunity i felt like i had i now have some means i can now make a deep investment uh in in lancaster city and actually build a house that's very you know very small um uh by i mean we're not really increasing the size we pushed up uh the roof a little bit but it's only the front so effectively we've turned a two-story house into two and a half story house um and so this is a very typical um city dwelling and the hope is to get be this will be the first uh house in lancaster county that will meet the passive house standard um jesse do you want to add a few comments my name is jesse pelman i run longview structures
our shop is on uh 400 block of south prince street we do quite a bit of work in town um and would also sort of say first off thank you to all of you for engaging in conversations one of the goals of this project uh is precisely to engage and to create dialogue around what housing can be uh most specifically what housing in urban environments in infill and what the reutilization of existing housing stock could look like so uh just for the sake of our sort of records uh keeping and our analysis of how we got to this point nate alluded to being somewhat surprised uh to being here we submitted a permit application as we do for all of our projects along with building elevations floor plans and a very short narrative of what the project was going to entail we had multiple back and forth with city staff including the inspector who was doing the plan review at the time had follow-up conversation with zoning specifically as it related to So at that time what was a proposed roof deck on the Lemon Street facade, there were 3D models that were associated with the permit submittal that showed what we were doing along with the extensive energy modeling that we were pursuing. So the after the fact characterization, while I fully acknowledge we are now evaluating a completely built out structure that is effectively from the exterior done, it was in no way intended to be nor was it and after the fact submittal we then followed up as the plan was developing as we were in process and as we were doing deep energy modeling we resubmitted plans and elevations that represent the current as-built condition to the city and to the city inspectors for additional review and for comment and receiving none and following through with site inspections we carried on with our work with the work as it had been permitted and authorized by the city so that's our our background it is not necessarily an after the fact in so much as we were trying to skirt or get around this opportunity as i mentioned we are looking for dialogue and for community and interaction one of the reasons that we have ended with the design that is currently up for debate is as nathan referenced our desire to reach a passive house certification which is an energy metric just an exceptionally miserly energy requirement for performance it is one of the most stringent building standards and requirements that exists there are currently none in the area that meet it there are specifically none in the area that meet it in an urban retrofit common wall application that we are attempting to undertake so the decision-making process and matrix that we entered into was robust it was intentional and it was thorough and we did our best to try to engage with city officials as we initiated the process and as it's gone throughout so one of the pieces that has come up for debate is how we hyper insulate and provide for future housing what a really basically zero energy house in the city can look like and one of the demands is insulation so i'll get a little technical please interrupt me ask questions at any point but the existing dormer in question was a vinyl clad uh vinyl sided dormer with what we call cheek walls that were about an inch and a half thick of no insulation and wood only the window in question was already replaced with a vinyl window there was no wood millwork the back roof of this structure had already been removed the stairs and access were non-code compliant unsafe and the roof was structurally unsound not that it was uninhabitable not that it was way outside the bounds of normal city housing stock but this i want to just set the character was not a particularly uh architecturally historic property in so much as the materials that were removed were of high value either monetarily or necessarily architecturally i do absolutely agree with the historic commission that we did interrupt the block so i will not dispute or try to counter the argument that we did break the continuity of a 14 dormer stretch again part of what we were looking to do is start dialogue so i have a crew there that works every day and there's hardly a day that goes by where somebody doesn't stop and say what's happening i've never seen this tell me about the project that's going on we've hosted regional events that is also looking for the future of housing how we can do housing in Lancaster well properly efficiently so while we are in conflict with the historic commission's report we got here somewhat unintentionally but at the same time we got here very much on purpose because we made a decision based on what we believe represents a possibility for moving forward and the architecture style of how we do that on the next one is certainly up for debate and had we gone through the process or been directed through the process at the initial plant's middle or if the city had requested additional feedback and information we would have gladly engaged at that time so happy to do that now i've talked a lot at you i really truly do want to have this primarily be conversation and dialogue but i want it to be understood in the context that this was a fully permitted fully green lighted city project that we are doing with the best intention of both city block city future and housing in mind so the characterization of after the fact i i bristle a little bit um and i also just want to characterize that we did not the vast majority of my company's work isn't historic preservation so you know we we do we fall into these camps where the world of preservation isn't inherently one of the most responsible sustainable ways to build part of the driver for this project was can we take that same mentality and push the envelope to this next level of potential development and can we get to one of the highest certifications that's out there in a Lancaster city home um rather than it's much easier out in cornfield we learned that today during some testing uh you know it's a very difficult very stringent um project that we're trying to thank
you thank you um so you said you mentioned that um you've been a contractor in lancaster city for quite a while yep and it never dawned on you to maybe go before the historical commission or check with the historical commission because you know a large portion of our city is historical
absolutely and we routinely run into suzanne we looked at where this property was it's an eclectic block it's outside of the harb all of these played into nate's desire to purchase the home and i don't want to we submit a lot of permits we are very much under the guidance of city permit clerk and city permit offices to follow their leading in their guidance we are often i can tell you anecdotal stories where we conflict with guidance because all of the code books are guidelines open to interpretation so i view my role as submitting all of the information at hand and then having that disseminated properly to the folks who need to review it and who need to stamp it and need to certify it and we do that to the best of our ability so we never withhold information we present it all out there for review and then
we respond accordingly okay thank you so much for the information my primary concern is that i mean there wasn't any thought of considering going through the historical commission or the historical review board to you know you know to look over your plans for the property and you know since you yourself said that you're i mean you've been a contractor in lancaster city for the longest time it would stand to reason that we might want to do that before we move forward
and that was part of the reason we actually did the follow-up plan submission midway through so we did go back we called in and said hey who who wants to see the plan review we were directed to give it to the inspector who was going to be doing the plan reviews that's where we sent it and so yeah i i acknowledge that it did not make it to suzanne that was not our intention to and withhold it from the historic commission or any other body that could get there um thank you are there any
other questions from the committee counselor craig um thank you for the explanation um curious about a couple things and i'm not sure who in this room could potentially answer this but specifically about the process so when you guys applied for the permits and received these permits you guys submitted drawings and set the expectation of what was going to be done and i'm assuming what
was applied for was completed that well yes so with the resubmission sure so we got a permit we realized part way through actually somewhat in response to uh city infrastructure planning and looking at the utilization of upper level stories um and the move to capture additional living space and density we said what's a responsible use we have this out of code compliance space that we can utilize and partly as a reaction to that decided to enlarge that third floor and then resubmitted plans and elevations showing existing conditions the initial plan that had been submitted and the revised plan that showed the new projections and elevation so it did come back through for review to the city gotcha and at that point
THE PERMIT WAS APPROVED WITH THE AFTER THE RESUMMISSION THE PERMIT HAD ALREADY BEEN APPROVED
PRIOR TO THAT AND WE RESUMMITTED AND SAID IS THERE ANYTHING THAT WE NEED TO DO WITH THIS AND GOT NO RESPONSE AND SO WE CONTINUED AND HAVE HAD INSPECTIONS OKAY YEAH I THINK FOR
ME PERSONALLY COUNCIL CRAIG I'M I THINK JUST FROM A PROCESS STANDPOINT I HAVE QUESTIONS AROUND IF A PERMIT WAS ISSUED WITH THE EXPECTATION OF THIS PROJECT HAPPENING IN THE WAY THAT IT HAPPENED WHAT HAPPENS WITH THE AFTER THE FACT DETERMINATION SO IF THE PROJECT'S ALREADY COMPLETED WHAT HAPPENS NOW IF COUNCIL WERE NOT TO APPROVE THIS TO MOVE FORWARD MAYBE THAT'S A GENERAL
QUESTION FOR SOMEONE ELSE TO ANSWER AS WELL YEAH MR FUNK SURE YOU CAN STEP UP TO THE MIC YEAH HI
MR FUNK UH I'M STEVE FUNK UH MEMBER OF THE HISTORICAL COMMISSION YOU CAN FEEL FREE TO
MOVE THAT UP AND DOWN TOO YOU CAN FEEL FREE TO MOVE THAT MIC STAND UP AND DOWN TOO IF IT IF IT IS LOW OR ON OR NOT, I'M NOT SURE.
REGARDING THE PERMIT, I DON'T KNOW IF YOU'VE ALL SEEN A PERMIT APPLICATION. IT INCLUDES BOXES THAT YOU CHECK THAT DESCRIBE THE DIFFERENT TYPES OF WORK THAT MAY OCCUR UNDER THE PERMIT. I ASSUME THE APPLICANT FILLED OUT THE PERMIT APPLICATION. THEY FAILED TO CHECK THE BOX FOR DEMOLITION OR ADDITION. AND THEN THE PERMIT WAS ACTUALLY listed as a permit for interior renovation that's why it wasn't flagged and sent to the historical commission first you know i'm hesitant to assign blame to that especially because no one from the the building department is here to state their position but there were some problems with the application and with the permit that was that was issued for interior renovation only and this
obviously was not interior renovation it did reference full window replacement it had three dimensional models of the exterior there's also a checklist on the front that we filled out in its entirety nowhere on the checklist does it ask us to go to the historic commission
so we did fill out a checklist well yeah that's that's not again that's not on the application yeah sure it is up to the building official to determine whether it goes to the historical COMMISSION OR NOT TO DETERMINE WHAT'S REVIEWABLE BUT IN THE HISTORICAL COMMISSION'S YOU KNOW VIEW THE PERMIT WAS ISSUED IN ERROR IT WAS AN ADMINISTRATIVE ERROR A CLARICAL ERROR YOU KNOW IT WAS THE WRONG KIND OF PERMIT THAT WAS ISSUED FOR OBVIOUSLY AN ADDITION YOU KNOW DEMOLITION AND A BUILDING ADDITION THAT'S NOT LISTED ON THE PERMIT OR THE APPLICATION
thank you are there any further questions from um from the committee or full council
council craig uh perhaps um a staff member could answer this question but just logistically what does it mean to deny an application after the fact could someone just talk to perhaps someone from the commission chris thank you good evening everyone um first of all
First of all I would like to say this is always a bad situation when we have a construction that was done in error. I do agree with Mr. Funk that there was an administrative error that was involved in this situation. We're also taking a closer look at how exactly this occurred. I do think there was were some abnormalities with with the application itself we're going to take a closer look at that I also have emails from as early as June where this was this problem was flagged among staff and I believe that it may have been raised with the applicant they can speak to this but as early as August so I'm I'm very confused about why the work continued after that point I would also I'm gonna check on this but I would take a little bit of issue with what Mr. Funk said we do have we do have protocols internally to try to make sure that we flag when something is reviewed needs to be reviewed by the Historical Commission however it's the responsibility of the property owner to determine if they need to go before the Historical Commission and unfortunately even if a building permit has been issued in error that does not necessarily absolve the applicant of needing to get that approval so I really feel bad for this situation that work has occurred and money has been spent again we try to avoid that at all costs at the same time this is a very egregious example of abuse of not abuse I'm sorry, of being out of character with the historical architecture on the block. I really appreciate what these gentlemen are trying to do from a green design standpoint, but that sustainable design can be done within the confines of good historical architecture and good historical design. I think one of the things that I would like to share with you all is a photo of the building, the construction, if you have not seen it yet. it is unfortunately it really does make a huge impact on the block I'm happy to do some additional analysis for you all with respect to what happened with the permit process but I think that there are also policy precedent questions here and and significant historic historic architectural loss on this block if this
were to stand thank you thank you director bill um speaking to the historical commission right now is there a resolution is there something that can be done in lieu of what they have
i guess i'll say we're tasked to review applications whether they meet uh the secretary of the junior group standards and the design standards and we're not REALLY TASKED WITH PROVIDING DESIGN SOLUTIONS OR RECOMMENDATIONS AT THIS POINT IN TIME, AND I WOULD FIND THAT PRETTY DIFFICULT WITH THIS APPLICATION. THANK YOU. ARE THERE ANY FURTHER
QUESTIONS FROM COUNSEL AS A WHOLE?
THANK YOU, COUNSELOR CRAIG. I GUESS MY ONLY QUESTION WOULD BE TO COUNSELOR CRAIG'S POINT, AND GIVEN THIS IS AFTER THE FACT, ARE THEY EXPECTED TO RETURN IT TO ITS ORIGINAL STATE?
THE HISTORICAL COMMISSION JUST LOOKS AT WHAT IS PRESENTED TO US. SO WE WERE PRESENTED WITH A DEMOLITION REQUEST AFTER THE FACT, AFTER IT WAS ALREADY DEMOLISHED, AND THEN WITH THE DESIGN. IF IT CAME TO US, LIKE JUST AS A BLUEPRINT, WE WOULD DENY IT. SO THAT'S WHY WE DENIED IT AS BUILT. AND I WILL SAY, BECAUSE MY BACKGROUND IS IN PRESERVATION CONSTRUCTION, IT IS VERY EASY TO FIGURE OUT IF A BUILDING IS IN THE HARB OR IN THE HISTORICAL COMMISSION. often will just go on the city website you can type in the address and see what zoning and what criteria it your that each address needs so that that's something that is not very hard to figure out if you need to do counselor
Craig if I may absolutely thank you I want to recognize the members of the Historical Commission for their work and understand that their role is really to review the Secretary of Interior standards and this presents a really interesting and unique challenge and and it's not one that's entirely uncommon uh to city council i remember a case in which um we've talked about dormers before we've talked about uh roofing materials uh et cetera et cetera but this is a a substantial change to the pattern of the dormers along this particular block of uh of lemon street and um and it is akin to sort of seeing a group of row homes where all the porches are open and then there's that one that's enclosed right in the middle of the block um and so i i i also want to acknowledge the ambitiousness of the certification program that you're going through and the efforts that you're taken to do something that's very unique in the city from a sustainability and a net zero energy project um i also acknowledge and i've never met you before jesse but i'm familiar that your business is located here in the city and i do see longview structure signs throughout the city and i know that um that you know you are conscientious in the work that you're doing there's a lot of different things that have happened in in this um in this particular circumstance what i'm going to suggest um to uh to to you counselor craig is a motion to table because i think that we need to have there's a if council is going to pursue a path in which there needs to be um uh the the roof uh the dormer needs to be returned to its original intention there are procedures i believe as it relates to the affordability and an applicant can share that information with council in terms of what the cost estimates are and have more information from which to make a decision i would also say that it's important for council to consider you know the internal operations of how this um you know in terms of the permit review and so on and so i will be following up with our internal department as well in terms of just the check boxes but this isn't just about the check box this is about a house that is going to ostensibly be forever changed by by by these renovations as good intentioned and as um you know forward thinking that they they are in terms of WHAT YOU'RE TRYING TO ACCOMPLISH SO THAT'S MY RECOMMENDATION I PROBABLY COULD HAVE GOTTEN TO THAT MORE QUICKLY BUT THANK YOU FOR HANGING WITH ME AS I'M A LITTLE THINKING A LITTLE BIT OUT LOUD
THANK YOU SO MUCH MAYOR COUNCILOR CRAIG IF I MAY OR SORRY GO AHEAD OH COUNCILOR COLLEAGUES
THANK YOU COUNCILOR GREG I'M WONDERING I'M NOT SURE WHO WOULD ANSWER THAT QUESTION WOULD IT BE POSSIBLE TO SUBMIT A NEW APPLICATION IF THEY FOLLOW THE HISTORICAL COMMISSION'S guidelines would you gentlemen be able to submit a new application we could submit a new application
one of the difficulties is we're done i would just go back to the comment why work continued work has not continued since we were notified of the issue so in august we were given permission to continue and carry on with interior work and non-visible work we have not done anything on that's front lemon street facing side so again we are doing our best to comply with the information that we are receiving from the city the what i would say potential difficulty in the new application is the decisions that we've made as part of this project are not easily undoable from either just a logistical standpoint or a financial standpoint the window that in question that faces lemon street is imported from austria it is not a run-of-the-mill window it is a deep investment in what good future housing uh is going to look at in terms of technology so we can argue the architecture we can argue the aesthetic all day long but the difficulty will be how we go backwards and still use the appropriate technology to meet these means so we could certainly resubmit it would represent significant time and financial impacts to the client and if we have to you know it's an active work site so we were hoping to be able to continue forward the city has made us aware that previously they said we can continue interior work but we were just notified that when we tried to schedule an interior inspection that they would not inspect until after this meeting so we have a unoccupied city house sitting mid-construction here as well which again represents a both time and finance constraint to the client yeah but it's also
important to follow the historical commission's recommendations in order to preserve the historical
aspects of the city's infrastructure and again i i do not dispute that i look at how we got to the eclectic block that this is where across the way we have distinctly different architecture on the bookends of the corner blocks it's an entirely different vernacular if you turn the corner uh we work on a property on lancaster avenue that's a church that's now a residence it's a hyper modern interior i think part of the beauty of a living vibrant city is the diversity in the block and so while i do fully acknowledge the loss of the repeating pattern of the dormer i would again couch it in that there was not particularly significance to it as an individual certainly to the block as a whole i would love to look at that as an opportunity and if we need to you know do a better job of education and inviting people to participate in that conversation that's you know one of the goals that we are looking to do here is to make this be something and it won't BE FOR EVERYBODY'S TASTE YOU KNOW SOME LIKE VICTORIAN HOUSES SOME COLONIAL SHAKER I THINK
THAT I WOULD RECOMMEND CONSULTED GREG TO TABLE THIS FOR NOW UNTIL YOU AND YOU GUYS AND THE HISTORICAL COMMISSIONS FIND A COMMON GROUND ON THAT THANK YOU YEAH GO AHEAD THANK YOU COUNCILOR
CRAIG I JUST WANT TO MAKE A COMMENT BECAUSE THIS VERY INTERESTING SITUATION THAT WE'RE IN SO when i want to be empathetic to the fact that uh it was mentioned that clerical error was made so i have um it's a little frustrating to feel that we're going to put the onus on a property owner uh to um a resident to have to correct that when uh it was something on our process that potentially could have prevented this um the other thing that i do want to mention why i think there i have a deep appreciation for our city's historical infrastructure i think the reality as well is that there are numerous conversations that are happening throughout our community around housing affordability energy consumption energy affordability and it's going to take innovative solutions to solve those challenges so um right now we have this tension between a historic housing stock uh which you know yes we we definitely should preserve and um also the need for innovation innovative solutions around housing affordability uh so it's interesting that this specific property um also is demonstrating this new idea that can save anywhere from 70 to 90 in energy costs which i find fascinating for a city that is suffering through a housing crisis and housing excuse me a housing affordability crisis and energy consumption can be um a big part of that so um yeah i just i want to make that comment i think uh given the fact that this is done i would also uh encourage and recommend mayor sirachi's recommendation around tabling this uh to ensure that you know we can come up with a good solution and move forward that honors um our CITY'S HISTORIC INTEGRITY BUT THEN ALSO UNDERSTANDS THAT YOU KNOW THERE ARE OPPORTUNITIES FOR NEW INNOVATIVE SOLUTIONS TO HOUSING AFFORDABILITY HERE THANK YOU COUNCILOR THANKS ARE THERE ANY
QUESTIONS OR COMMENTS FROM THE PUBLIC THIS IS ON OKAY IT'S ACTUALLY AT MY LEVEL I'm Susie Hoover I have a house at 204 East King Street 1787 when I redid that house a number of years ago people tried to sell me replacement windows this that and the other thing and I retained the original windows I had them redone I'm not even well painted and that sort of thing a specialty insulation window on storm window on that and I would say with an old house that age and I took efforts with the best heating the last air conditioning that I could my utility bills on that house are very low and people come into my house and they tell me how incredibly quiet it is for being right on the frontage of East King Street which it is and so I think there are ways of accomplishing staying historic with materials that are very conducive to these type of renewal of historic homes without making major deviation from regulations for historic homes thank you
thank you miss hoover tony dasher 700 block of new holland avenue i i don't think the city's process failed them here uh as mr fung pointed out and i get it it was a it was a check mark but right now we're living in a country where people are being deported over check marks on forms this is honestly a situation which i understand the complications but something was filled out wrong and the process was followed incorrectly and that stuff happens uh i think we do need to be mindful of our historic architecture but i've even said to some people like we don't need to preserve every single house in lancaster city for its historic nature if we're trying to be a city IT DEVELOPS SO I THINK ME AS A MEMBER OF THE PUBLIC I'M OPEN TO CHANGE I DON'T UNDERSTAND THE FULL CONTEXT OF YOUR SITUATION BUT I WANT TO DEFEND THE CITY HERE AND SAY LIKE I DON'T THINK THAT THEIR PROCESS WAS WRONG THIS WAS A I'M GOING TO ASSUME TO BE A GENUINE ERROR UM AND I HOPE FOR YOU ALL THE BEST IN NAVIGATING THIS GOING FORWARD BUT SORRY THANK YOU MR ESTRA ARE THERE ANY FURTHER
questions from the public or comments hearing none um i'd like to make a motion to table this um resolution their historical review until we can investigate much further all those in favor aye aye thank you thank you gentlemen all right the next item on our agenda this evening is ADMINISTRATION RESOLUTION NUMBER 65-2025. AUTHORIZING A COOPERATION AGREEMENT FOR GRANT FUNDING WITH THE LANCASTER COUNTY HOUSING AND REDEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY. DIRECTOR CAMPBELL.
TINA CAMPBELL. I PROMISE I WILL NOT TALK AS LONG AS I DID WHEN I WAS UP HERE BEFORE. BUT THIS IS A REQUIRED AGREEMENT FROM THE PENNSYLVANIA OFFICE OF THE BUDGET FOR THE REDEVELOPMENT ASSISTANCE Assistance Capital Program Grant, or RACP. This is a grant that the Lankester County Redevelopment Authority was awarded for the reconstruction that's happening at the former Redmond site at 800 South Queen Street. For RACP grants, a municipality or a municipal authority must apply for the funding. So even if it is a community benefit organization or a developer, it must go through a municipality OR A MUNICIPAL AUTHORITY. GENERALLY THE MUNICIPALITY WHERE THE ORGANIZATION IS LOCATED OR WHERE THE PROJECT IS LOCATED WILL APPLY, BUT IN THIS CASE AND IN OTHER CASES, TOO, THE CITY HAS ASKED LANGSTER COUNTY REDEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY TO APPLY JUST BASED ON CAPACITY TO DO THOSE APPLICATIONS. SO THE GRANT APPLICATION WAS AWARDED BY THE OFFICE OF THE BUDGET, THE PENNSYLVANIA OFFICE OF THE BUDGET BACK IN 2023, I BELIEVE. AND BECAUSE THE HOST municipality so the host municipality of the project in this case us we were not the applicant the office of the budget requires a cooperative agreement between the applicant and the municipal authority that's doing the project or this that's working with the grant so it's a it's basically an agreement that should the authority not do what they're supposed to do to ensure prompt payment of the grant to the to the organization that's supposed to be receiving it the city needs to work with the authority to ensure that that payment goes where it BE GOING IT DOESN'T OBLIGATE US TO ACTUALLY PAY FUNDS OR REALLY INDEED INCUR ANY FINANCIAL TRANSACTIONS EVEN A PASS THROUGH TRANSACTION SO IT'S NO FINANCIAL TRANSACTIONS FOR THE CITY WE'VE SIGNED THIS AGREEMENT FOR A FEW OTHER GRANTS MOST RECENTLY WAS LAST YEAR FOR THE LGH EXPANSION WHICH HAS BEEN COMPLETED WE'VE NEVER NEEDED TO ENFORCE OR DO ANYTHING WITH THIS AGREEMENT THE AUTHORITY IS VERY WELL VERSED IN MANAGING RAPI FUNDING they handle a lot more than we do each year for the county thank you director campbell are there
any questions about this resolution from the committee no no questions or comments from the public hearing none i'll make a motion to move resolution 65 to full council on the 14th second okay all those in favor all right hi thank you the next item on our agenda this evening is resolution 66 and i'm noticing that 66 and 67 are local shares accounts is it okay if we do them together we might we do okay all right authorizing the application to local shares account program by
10-fold. Dan, I'm sorry, you may need to hit that button to turn your mic on. You're very good at projecting, but that's it. Thank you. Great. I'm here on behalf of 10-fold requesting $100,000 from the local shares account to purchase a 15-passenger van. This van will directly support client services in a number of ways. It will serve the transportation needs of 10-fold's shelter and housing stability programs at any given time there are 190 households in tenfold programs that could benefit from transportation in each of these programs case managers provide services to individuals and families experiencing homelessness in lancaster county many of these households face transportation barriers limiting access to things like employment opportunities health care housing appointments and food banks a 15 passenger van would also serve as a means for households without transportation to access tlc emergency shelter when they cannot get there on their own we also envision using this for logistical supports as well moving supplies between different sites and really to facilitate in building positive community and positive experiences among our case managers and and clients and and in the households themselves having the ability to take people on educational outings, attending local events, volunteering, all of which promote connections, strengthen relationships, and build community. We believe that a 15-passenger van aligns with the LSA's goal of enhancing community, well-being, and infrastructure, and it will allow Tenshold staff to safely and reliably transport clients to critical destinations, which we believe will shorten the length of time people experience homelessness and that we feel like is a win for everybody
thank you I'm gonna ask if director Campbell can come and give us a brief overview so that we can just review what local shares are and where they come
from I'm gonna actually just introduce you to Jen Arantes who is our development manager and she handles all the LSA grants so she's gonna give you a
wonderful perfect again I'm Jen and the purpose of the statewide LSA program is to reinvest gaming funds into projects in the communities to improve quality of life across Pennsylvania so specifically these grants range anywhere from twenty five thousand to one million dollars and there's no local match required funding can be used to support public infrastructure community facilities equipment vehicle purchases demolition and planning and design work so a lot of the benefits that comes to the communities that apply and receive LSA funding it brings outside investment into projects that might otherwise be unfunded improves neighborhood facilities and services and creates opportunities for partnerships specifically because the city needs to apply for any nonprofits or other organizations who are interested in THESE PROGRAMS SO SINCE 2022 WHEN WE WERE FIRST ABLE TO APPLY FOR THESE GRANTS WE AS A CITY HAVE SUBMITTED 30 APPLICATIONS 11 HAVE BEEN AWARDED AND WE'RE STILL WAITING FOR 2024 APPLICATIONS IN TOTAL LANCASTER CITY HAS RECEIVED 5.9 MILLION IN AWARDED DOLLARS THROUGH THE LSA PROGRAM AND IN 2025 WE'RE EXPECTING TO SUBMIT 11 MORE THANK YOU SO MUCH ARE THERE ANY QUESTIONS FROM
THE COMMITTEE ON THE LOCAL SHARES.
I HAVE ONE CLARIFICATION THAT MIGHT BE IMPORTANT CONTEXT. ALSO, THANK YOU FOR YOUR APPLICATION. I THINK IT'S A VERY WORTHY PROJECT. BUT JUST ABOUT THE LOCAL SHARES PROCESS, ALTHOUGH WE SUBMIT THE APPLICATION ON BEHALF OF THE ORGANIZATIONS, DO WE HAVE ANY SORT OF FIDUCIARY RESPONSIBILITY OR OVERSIGHT IF THEY ARE TO BE AWARDED?
WE DO NOT. SO WE SIGN WITH ANY AWARDED ORGANIZATION, WE SIGN AN MOU WITH THEM, BASICALLY STATING that we are there for um support for grant support and that all of the then reimbursements come through us um but we are not we are not the the owners of those dollars it comes from the state
directly thank you wonderful um i'm gonna make a motion that we move um resolution 66 to full council on the 14th second all those in favor aye thank you thank you um the next item on our agenda is resolution 67 2025 authorized an application to local shares account program
by the ywca good evening good evening my name is dana clark i'm actually the architect for the y forward renovations i'm here on behalf of stacy tonight she was able to make it but i want to thank council and the mayor for allowing us this opportunity this is as you may know a transformational project for the YWCA their historic building and quite honestly that that corner of the city at this point if you haven't been by recently we're about 95% complete if you're looking for a historic building with a facelift go check out this one we're super excited for having been able to remove the stair tower and restore the facade of that building so if you haven't been by please please take it take a walk and take a look I have promised everyone on staff there that they will be in before Thanksgiving if they don't they promised they would cook me so in our in the next steps for this in this first there were two other previous phases that we did some with LSA funding. This phase, we're going to welcome new tenants, 17. We've added 17 units of low-income housing and then refurbished 12 existing residential suites in the existing building. What we're looking for now, the request before you, is to support phase four, which is the last phase of this really ambitious project um this last phase will renovate all the additional residential suites that have not been touched by any of the three previous phases it will enhance livability and efficiency we talked a little bit about energy efficiency it is key in making an older building work well part of what we're doing is increasing the efficiency of all the units and phase four continues to do that on the fourth floor uh which is the location of of the remaining units that need to be renovated. The second floor, another key component is the childcare component. The second floor is going to get reorganized and renovated. Again, not only improved utilities, HVAC lighting, but also better layout to support more programs for the daycare center. So we're excited. We're excited by that. It will increase the overall capacity of the Y and its program, which is something that they really do need. The first floor, so the phase four is really the fourth floor, the second floor, and some additional work on the first floor. The work on the first floor, if you guys have been in there, you know there's an old gymnasium that was in there. Similar to what we did when we filled in the old auditorium space, we're looking to get more square footage in this urban environment, and there's nowhere for them to go so the best use of that existing facility would be to add another floor there and again this is all to increase the childcare program so all the work that we're doing I know they'll be very excited to show you all at the open house all the work we're doing is very sensitive to historic fiber inside the building and outside the building so while it's you know it's unfortunate to infill a volume space I think in this particular case it makes sense for the why and their programming and again the first floor lay out some of the lobby if you guys have been in the lobby you know has had some less sensitive work done to it the last piece of phase four is to take certain portions of that lobby that are really open to the public and for community use and sort of restore those pieces back to a more historically sensitive context so the full cost for phase four is projected at seven million phase three is gonna finish they've already spent or will be spending at the end of phase three 11 million so the Y has invested significant resources not only through grant programs like the LSA but you know Stacy has done a phenomenal job of looking for other in other forms of revenue to support the mission and the programs at the Y so I was pretty excited that she asked me to come in and
help with this one you guys have any questions thank you i have one question how many total units
will be in the y so there's going to be on the i think there are and you're going to ask me that i'm going to guess and don't hold me to this because it's i don't have my drawings with me i'm going to guess there's an additional 18 additional 24 units on the fourth floor that'll be wound into this so that takes it to 52 53 so um you know and they vary there's all different types of units so we have accessible units we have essentially sro units which think of old style dorm rooms right some have their some have little kitchenettes inside some have their own bathrooms inside some use a shared facility so i think they're touching they're trying to hit as many points of need as possible and i think you know one of the ways to to do that is if everyone has a great room that they can call their own even if this has a shared restroom if you go through this you'll see the shared ref rooms are really quite nice so i think they're doing their best to expand the program and accommodate as many folks as need their help as possible and they're doing it with all different types of unit configurations thank you so much are there
ANY QUESTIONS FROM THE COMMITTEE? THANK YOU FOR BEING HERE TONIGHT. WHAT CAN YOU TELL US ABOUT THE TIMELINE OF THIS PROJECT?
THE PROTECTION FOR PHASE FOUR? PHASE THREE IS DUE TO FINISH IN NOVEMBER OF THIS YEAR. PHASE FOUR, THIS IS ONE PIECE OF A LARGER PUZZLE AS IT RELATES TO FUNDING. SO I THINK STACY'S GOALS ARE TO HAVE DRAWINGS UNDERWAY IN 2026 FOR PHASE FOUR, WHICH WOULD PUT US INTO A 2027 START FOR PHASE FOUR. THANK YOU.
YOU'RE WELCOME. ARE THERE ANY FURTHER
QUESTIONS FROM COUNSEL AS A WHOLE, QUESTIONS OR COMMENTS?
COUNSELOR NIETZ. THANK YOU, COUNSELOR CRAIG. I just wanted to commend you. I was a counselor for sexual assault years ago, so seeing it grow and seeing it build, it's great. It just feels good knowing that women that run into situations of sexual assault or not having a home, it's great to know where they can go.
Thank you. And I think that's always been our goal. When they built the building, it was supposed to be as nice for the people that were coming to use it as it was for someone that was wealthy that lived in the city and what we've really tried to do is take that same level of care and and bring it to the new and restore the structure so it's doing the same thing regardless so appreciate you hearing that thank you i'll make
a motion that we move resolution 67 to full council on the 14th second all those in favor aye thank you so much thank you um the last item on our agenda this evening is council bill number 10 2025 amending the zoning ordinance to address data centers good evening all
hi yeah director dells have you connected using that before okay david's gonna help you
with a quick little install don't forget to hit your button there you're going to spread
good evening everybody sorry for the delay i was looking for my speaker notes but we're going to go with plan b and use the hard copy instead um okay um well uh thank you for the opportunity uh to speak on this topic tonight i know there's been a lot of interest in data centers overall um and particularly uh subject of zoning um uh first uh i think all of you know me i'm chris delfs i'm the director of community planning and economic development uh but wanted to introduce myself again um for uh public in the room as well uh also wanted to turn it over just for a moment so that uh betsy can introduce herself as well good evening i'm betsy logan i'm the planning bureau chief for the city okay um i think i'm going to do most of the talking but um betsy's the technical expert here in a number of the these areas so she may assist with some parts of the presentation and answer uh questions as well um okay uh should we jump in absolutely good okay um just wanted to start with with where we've been uh on august 26 city council directed staff and the solicitor's office to develop a zoning ordinance to specifically address data centers in the city of lancaster our chief planner betsy who you just met and i have been working on the draft ordinance since that time in august in concert with our city solicitor and also we have outside land use council that we use for important matters such as these during that time we've researched best practices we've spoken to experts we've connected with other other municipalities, and generally attempted to build our knowledge about data centers, both their challenges and their opportunities. Please note, this is the first draft of the ordinance, which will undergo additional rounds of review and feedback. So normally, I end a presentation with process. I don't usually start with process, but I think in this case, it's really important. So we're clear about where we're headed. formulating zoning code was designed to be deliberative in other words it is a slow process by nature i think the state and the local legislature has contemplated that this is intended to be a slow slow process so that it's well thought through before we make changes to our zoning code typically this type of work the research and the development of this kind of ordinance takes in in the realm of three to four months uh staff have expedited our work at the request of council and most importantly this is an important community issue that has a sense of urgency here um on this slide i i wanted to talk about the zoning process in in general uh here on the left whether uh this is a data center consideration or any kind of change to the zoning ordinance there are steps that we must go through as staff and as a city government the first is essentially the introduction of the zoning ordinance the zoning amendment that's what's happening here tonight this is the first presentment to to the city council committee in addition to that there is a review and comment or recommendation by the city planning commission and by the county planning commission there is also a public hearing that is required by law typically that happens before city council that's how we have done done this in the past and then because it's an ordinance and not a resolution it requires at least it requires the two readings before council and ultimately a vote and adoption if that's what you so choose moving on to how that applies to this particular zoning ordinance for the data centers there are a couple dates that we know for sure right now. The first is tonight October 6th. The second date is we have told our city planning commission that after tonight we will be sharing the ordinance draft with them and that they will have an opportunity to discuss this ordinance draft ordinance on October 15th as well. There is a mandatory 45-day review process with the county staff and county planning Commission. We can come back and talk about that later if it's valuable, but I just wanted to note that here. Ultimately, we also have to have the hearing and the two readings before council that I mentioned. These dates have not been set in stone yet, but we have considered that they would occur probably in the end of October or during the month of December. For the most part tonight, WE'RE GOING TO TALK ABOUT DATA CENTERS IN GENERAL AND HOW THIS ZONING ORDINANCE WOULD IMPACT DATA CENTERS THROUGHOUT THE CITY. HOWEVER, WE ALL KNOW THAT TWO DATA CENTERS HAVE BEEN PROPOSED IN THE CITY AT THIS TIME. ONE IS ON GREENFIELD ROAD AND ONE IS ON HARRISBURG PIKE. I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT TO TALK ABOUT THE ZONING MAP AND MAYBE TO A CERTAIN EXTENT the comprehensive plan future land use map as well the um the location or the data center that has been proposed at the greenfield road location is in the suburban manufacturing zoning district the map on the left you can see it's in the top right corner in the blue color and then the harrisburg pike location is in that lavender color it's in the central manufacturing zoning district and it's sort of in the top left, fairly close to Longs Park. So one of the things I just wanted to say in general here, I think there may be more questions about this, but it is not lawful for us as a municipality to exclude any particular land use in the city, including data centers. Our comp plan and our zoning ordinance determines where specific uses are best suited. So I know there has been a lot of consternation about the zoning determination related to the Greenfield Road site, for example. I know there's some granular issues there at play, but just wanted to start with the suburban manufacturing zoning district itself. I want to read you the definition from that particular zoning district in our zoning code. Okay. So again, this is suburban manufacturing. not a lot of uh this district does not cover a lot of land in the city but this is where the 216 greenfield road is located the suburban manufacturing district is intended to accommodate the most intense industrial uses which have greater land area requirements and need for close proximity to regional transportation networks including railway and limited access highways there's more there related to other commercial and retail uses but i think that that applies most to what we're talking about here in the case of a data center before we jump into the content of the ordinance I think you all have a copy of the draft ordinance in front of you and I believe it's been shared with the audience as well and we'll get into some of the components of that ordinance shortly I would like to acknowledge the work that community stakeholders have already done here for example we have read and incorporated ideas from example ordinances that were provided to us some time ago mr kenneth weeks who's one of our city planning commissioners provided us some information an example we also took a look at the document that mr arcolio provided to city at the last city council meeting as well and that along with a lot of of other resources that we've looked at have gone into this process. I'm going to take the ordinance a piece at a time. We're not going to have time to go through every word or every section, but I do want to highlight parts of it because I think it will be helpful for the dialogue. First of all, as with any ordinance, we start with the whereas clauses. The intent here is to frame the purpose and need of this change to our code. Question one is the definition of the data center, and this part is important. So per the draft ordinance, a data center is a facility whose primary purpose is to centralize storage, processing, management or dissemination of digital data, information or applications. This includes but is not limited to server farms, cloud computing hubs, co-location centers and telecommunications switching hubs. Data centers typically house large-scale computer systems and supporting infrastructure, such as backup generators, cooling systems, and uninterruptible power supplies. A data center generally includes environmental controls, such as air conditioning and fire suppression, redundant-slash-backup power supplies, redundant data communications connections, and high security. There's a lot there. There's a lot to consider, and I wanted to read the definition because it's important as we consider how we're dealing with these different parts of what a data center actually is. In addition to that, the next part of the ordinance is related to the table of permitted uses. You can see here, this is an excerpt from the manufacturing and industrial portion of the table that governs the acceptable uses here. Essentially, what this is saying is that data centers would be prohibited or not allowed in any of the zoning districts throughout the city, with the exception of suburban manufacturing and central manufacturing. Now, in this proposal, that use, data centers, would not be allowed by right. They would be allowed by special exception. And that applies to the content, really, of the rest of the ordinance here data centers would only be granted that special exception by the zoning hearing board through the meaning of those of the standards that are outlined here are detailed here in the zoning ordinance I know this is very dense so I'm going to take a pause there that was really the first introduction framing of the data of the data center ordinance before we start to get into more of the details related to uh the standards uh do council members have any
questions at this time okay so my question is related to the noise is there like i know that they have decibels levels um and i'm not sure the acoustic i'm thinking that you would have like 85 55 to 85 DB's is that something that would be outside or is it around 95 or 96 do you have what levels they'll be because I'm sure that those that live close by especially the one on Harrisburg Pike especially that they have mentioned the fact that they want to know how loud that is going to be
Yeah. Councillor Diaz, thank you for the question. And if you don't mind, I'm going to circle back to that very briefly. Before I jump into the noise category, I just wanted to call your attention to the slide that is up now. That is section three of the ordinance, and it includes all of these different topic areas. The first topic area is actually noise, and we can take some time to speak about that i just wanted to show that um this this really represented the uh the rest of of the
ordinance content here council craig um director delphs um first things first um at your convenience if you could please forward the slide deck to council as we don't have access to our screens this evening we don't we haven't we don't but second the definition of data center can you talk about how you arrived at that definition was it derived from other sources is it a common
definition how did we arrive at that yeah it is a fairly common definition we've been working with Lancaster County Planning Commission on getting ordinances that have been approved or in the PROCESS OF BEING PROVED WITHIN THE COUNTY AND SO WE UTILIZE THAT ORDINANCE OF AS WELL AS LIKE RESEARCH THAT'S BEEN DONE UM MOSTLY IN VIRGINIA BECAUSE THEY HAVE SO MANY AND THEY REALLY ARE KIND OF IN THEIR SECOND OR THIRD ROUND OF UPDATES TO THEIR ORDINANCES TO MAKING SURE THEY'RE
ADDRESSING EVERYTHING GREAT THANK YOU ANY FURTHER QUESTIONS FOR COUNCIL I'M SORRY COUNCIL PRESIDENT
I JUST WANT TO MAKE SURE I UNDERSTOOD YOUR REQUEST WERE YOU SAYING THAT YOU WOULD LIKE
me to send it later on or would you like me to forward it if perhaps uh betsy if you have access to it or i see okay rebecca has it that would be great that way we could have it in real time
so okay perfect great yeah yeah thank you okay shall i keep rolling keep going okay thank you as i showed in that last table there are a lot of sections we're not going to go through each of those sections tonight but i did want to call out a handful of those sections that we have heard a lot of concern from from the public directly both council meetings and through other avenues as well uh the first topic is noise uh so thank thank you again counselor diaz um what what we're trying to do here in the ordinance there's actually two parts one requires a noise mitigation plan that's submitted with the zoning application so that's looking at a holistic approach to minimizing or mitigating noise in part two it also says there shall be no noise disturbance as that term is defined in the city city's noise control ordinance so what we're trying to do here is link it to an ordinance that already exists from our standpoint we do think that the noise ordinance that we have in place is a strong ordinance if you uh it is not your question was about decibel level that is one way that we could go as staff as a council uh what we have proposed so far is to really um focus on the the impact of the residents not the measurement and so noise disturbance as uh as defined in the noise ordinance is uh any sound specified in another part of the ordinance or any sound which, A, endangers or injures the safety or health of humans or animals, B, annoys or disturbs a reasonable person of normal sensitivities, or C, endangers or injures personal or real property. So that's how we've proposed to handle it so far. As I said, there are different ways to approach this, and the ordinance will continue to evolve here through the process. TO THE NEXT TOPIC HERE IS AIR QUALITY. THAT IS SECTION 3B. WE HAVE TWO PARTS HERE TO THE AIR QUALITY SECTION. PART ONE STATES THAT BACKUP POWER EQUIPMENT SHALL MINIMIZE AIR POLLUTANT EMISSIONS AND MEET OR EXCEED APPLICABLE STATE AND FEDERAL LAWS REGULATING EMISSIONS. IN THE CASE THAT BACKUP GENERATORS ARE USED, EPA TIER 4 EMISSION STANDARDS OR EQUIVALENT MUST BE must be achieved also section b 2 annual testing shall be performed and reports shall be provided to the city and other relevant state and federal agencies to ensure that data center equipment is performing as designed and emissions from the data center do not exceed allowable limits one of the things to note here is that air quality is governed by a state process it's a air quality permit that is managed by the department of environmental protection we can come back to that later in the presentation the third item here on the slide is section c energy use and again section c has two parts part one data centers shall make good faith efforts to maximize use of renewable and or clean energy for all electrical and cooling needs either through on-site generation or verifiable power purchase agreements part two c2 an emergency management plan shall be submitted uh i'm sorry an energy management plan shall be submitted with the zoning application detail detailing at a minimum annual electricity demand what supply sources will be utilized energy storage capacity and efforts made to maximize use of renewable renewable or clean energy this is another area that we actually have discussed this one at length with our solicitor and this is a difficult area to regulate through zoning law through zoning ordinance I think there's more more to talk about here in terms of how we have discussed this issue with the developer Carissa and again come back to that later the last topic that I elected to call out here in the slide is section D water utilization and d part 1 states a water utilization report shall be submitted with the zoning application detailing at a minimum the total daily intake volume and sources of that water discharge volumes and destinations cooling system type and efficiency and and shall demonstrate compliance with the city's stormwater ordinances and regulations. One of the things that is also important to note here is that this water use is not governed by zoning alone. It is governed by a number of other city approvals. And as you may have seen in a recent Lancaster newspaper article, there are decisions that are made by the Susquehanna River Basin Commission related to how much water can be used for a particular project. One of the things that we've talked about here is making sure that we're not seeing water use grow beyond a certain level. And again, we'll come back to that. There are several other sections in the zoning ordinance that are more typical for a zoning ordinance that we see throughout other kinds of uses, not data centers alone. Most of these are related to physical design issues. So there are examples related to parking, setbacks, yard buffers, screening. All these are very important issues, but perhaps a little more straightforward because zoning is used to regulate these items. If you have questions about any of these particular topics, we can come back to them. And then last but not least, we have a couple sections at the end of the ordinance that are not necessarily physical design, but there are other priorities that we thought were important to include in zoning ordinance. One is a requirement for an emergency management plan. That is section M. And then lastly, section N is related to community engagement. And that states that the developer of the data center shall hold a public informational meeting prior any zoning hearing board or planning commission review as you know and as part of this process you see there are a lot of opportunities for public to engage through a formal board or commission or city council this is an additional requirement in addition to those processes turning our attention from the zoning amendment for a moment we are not ready to discuss the details of a community benefits agreement with the developer Carissa tonight but it is important to note that work is happening in tandem on the zoning amendment and the community benefits agreement there's a lot of crossover among these topics and we've been trying to work carefully and thoughtfully about how these things interact I believe that the administration and mayor sirachi will have some additional updates about the community benefits agreement later in the month again not quite ready to talk about that and i also don't want to muddy the waters and confuse things because we're really here to focus on the zoning amendment tonight coming back to these four topics noise air quality energy and water we are working to ensure that we understand and minimize noise disturbance. Carissa has already told us that they're designing toward ensuring that data centers do not increase ambient noise levels. Of course, this is going to take work to make sure that this is documented and memorialized, but that is what we are hearing so far. In addition, the data center facilities have been designed to meet all requirements of a minor air quality permit, as determined by the Pennsylvania Department of Environmental protection the city is engaged in that process with DEP and we're interacting with them directly we've been asking questions we've been following up on a number of different things related to the design and operation of the backup generators that again is regulated entirely by the state DEP although the city does does play a role in serving as a party and providing our comments to With respect to energy, I did want to share that there are a variety of electric infrastructure investments that will be required as part of the data centers that have been proposed. At this point, Carissa has been in conversation and negotiation with PPL and will be establishing which of those facilities will be which will be paid for by Carissa essentially the the intent there is that Carissa will be covering the costs of any electrical power infrastructure that is directly serving their data centers and in addition to that there are potential benefits to strengthening the local power grid as well finally with respect to the water utilization uh as as i mentioned before there was a recent article about the sustain uh susquehanna um river basin commission and chryssa have reported to them and they have reported to us city administration uh that they will be remaining under 20 000 gallons per day per data center campus so there's a campus proposed at greenfield road again and a campus proposed at harrisburg pike each of those we've been told will remain under 20 000 gallons again this is all this is all based upon uh dialogue and uh conversation what has to come next is related to documentation and the community benefits agreement there are other topics and issues that would come in the cba but uh wanted to connect these topics from the zoning amendment to the cba okay i'm gonna i'm gonna pause there again uh and see if there are additional questions i do want i do want to bring us back to to the process and again recognize that uh happy to answer any questions we have tonight but it is very possible that the zoning uh amendment the zoning ordinance amendment may evolve through these other steps in the process
as well great um council president thank you um dr delphs uh under specifically water utilization and perhaps this is similar to energy use and and you know and the noise uh the way we've uh the approach we're taking with this yes um is it possible it to put an actual limitation on water usage in the zoning ordinance itself is that a thing no no it's not a thing council president
unfortunately because um we that would be regulating businesses ostensibly because the zoning ordinance has to be agnostic in terms of one category of uses cannot conflict with another category of uses and so we are we are precluded from putting in a specific limitation related to water but as director delfts mentioned there are other um policies related to water utilization and then there is also the susquehanna river basin commission and then um you know i think just to put a pin a finer point on what director delfts is saying is that um there are community there are conversations that are happening related to the community community benefits agreement that will go beyond the zoning ordinance and so i'll i'll be prepared to talk about those later and be able to con to contrast the zoning text amendment with the community benefits agreement but for the purposes of a zoning text amendment we have to be we have to tread very carefully because we cannot preclude any use in the city and we also cannot put a burden on one particular use over another use so for example requiring the data center to not use more than 20 000 gallons of water or to require them to use a particular source of energy those are two examples and i will just say that we um zoning has strengths and limitations i will also
add we've had a lot of very uh healthy discussions and wrestling matches with uh our with our solicitor uh and with our outside land use council trying to ask all of these questions and understanding what uh zoning ordinance will ultimately be the most effective and and also DEFENSIBLE THAT WILL THAT WILL HOLD UP UNDERSTOOD THANK YOU COUNCILOR MOOD THANK YOU COUNCILOR
CRAIG AND THANK YOU DIRECTOR DELVES AND CITY STAFF FOR YOUR THOROUGHNESS IN THIS ZONING AMENDMENT MY QUESTION IS IF APPROVED WILL THIS RETROACTIVELY APPLY TO THE TWO DATA CENTERS THAT ARE CURRENTLY
BEING PROPOSED THIS IS IS THE QUESTION THAT EVERYONE HAS BEEN INTERESTED IN AND UNFORTUNATELY I don't have a satisfactory answer right now because the sincere answer is that the city does not yet have a definitive legal position on whether this zoning amendment would apply to these two sites. There are a number of moving parts that are happening right now and reasonable attorneys could disagree about when this would apply. So the official position right now is that we are not sure yet. And so it's important that we're doing as good a job as possible on the zoning amendment and that we're continuing to have good dialogue with Carissa, who so far has negotiated in in good faith and has been, I have found them so far to be a sincere partner in those conversations.
Thank you. And my final question, which you just mentioned, is the text amendment states that data centers shall make good faith efforts to maximize use of renewable and or clean energy. Other than the verifiable power purchase agreements, what other metrics do we have to show that
they're acting in good faith yeah I appreciate the question and this is where we were trying to stretch into some territory to ensure that a developer this developer or any future developer of a data center that they are required to be intentional and thoughtful and put together an energy management plan that tries to achieve these goals yeah it would be very difficult for us to hold a developer to say a specific percentage of renewable energy that's one thing that we've talked about as staff internally for example um one of the things that we've also talked about as a goal is trying to ensure that there is limited to no fossil fuel use many of these data centers because of the huge energy draw that they require are looking to use nuclear power and there are different opinions about nuclear power it is considered a cleaner source of fuel obviously it does come with other other challenges but I do think that any data most data centers in the country now are seeking to use nuclear power at least as some part of their power portfolio and
also renewable as we've seen the three billion dollar purchase of hydro power by Google on the Susquehanna River over the next 20 years so that I think that there's a combination of factors and that are at play here in terms of the the power utilization or the power source and also pushing up against the limits of what we can accomplish in a zoning text amendment thank you and I
appreciate the work being done by your department and by city staff and I would just hope that we continue to think about ways to protect city residents
against vague good faith effort definitions yep i we we agree and uh that is there to require that there's planning and there's thinking um but we are continuing to push on the issue of renewable as the mayor mentioned i i think that's very important are there any further questions from
council as a whole councilor hirsch uh thank you director delfts um kind of a question kind of a comment and it might come across as odd but I know for me and as far as evaluating you know what the zoning can do and and what the city can do and regulate and as far as what some of my concerns are I would say noise is definitely one that I have and I would just hope that the city would consider evaluating that at night and um and during the day because i know there's been talk about other ambient sound kind of um that it being neutral with that sound but um just making sure that we're evaluating that at all times of the day because these are operating um you know 24 7.
Councilor Diaz. In relations to the noise again, has anybody from the administration gone to another data center to hear or to see what the frequency is or what the decimals, what the acoustics are like? I'm just curious if that was a possibility. I can take that, Chris.
Sure. Director Delves. What I would say, Councillor Diaz is that we have hired outside expertise that has worked both representing communities concerned about noise from data centers as well as data center developers themselves who have to meet certain standards related to noise to address the design of these facilities to ensure that that noise is not a factor and so while While city staff have not taken the time to drive or go to another site, we have actually hired expertise in this regard to assist us in making sure that their noise analysis is being independently reviewed by a third party and reported back to the administration. I believe that that process is happening this week and next week for both of the foot for the phase one and phase two that are contemplated at Greenfield so this is to say that we are not relying on our expertise we're relying on the EXPERTISE OF FOLKS WITH A LOT MORE EXPERIENCE IN APPROACHING THESE PROJECTS IN A WAY THAT IS SENSITIVE TO THE AMOUNT OF NOISE THAT CAN BE GENERATED BY THEIR USE.
THANK YOU. I'LL TAKE QUESTIONS AND
COMMENTS FROM THE PUBLIC. CAN YOU FIRST START WITH YOUR name and your block of residence my name is matthew barden i'm on the 800 block of north prince thank you we can see this this document tacitly acknowledges the numerous potential downsides of this facility to the community energy and water use and pollution chief among them to all acknowledge the glaring lack of detail around the proposed limits of this facility at this time what i'm failing to see is the benefit to the city at large or any individual residents of lancaster this kind of facility creates no meaningful number of community jobs provides no necessary or desired local service. Any argued tax benefits to the community would ignore the long-standing tradition in this country of corporate entities evading their responsible tax burdens to the local community, and even ignoring that, pale in comparison to the litany of medical issues that these facilities have already proven to lead to in the short term, and that doesn't even account the currently unproven long-term environmental and health impacts. There's no amount of financial benefit offered by these data centers that could conceivably offset the corresponding detriment to public health and welfare. It's very easy to find
stories about communities that have suffered because of these data centers but i've yet to
see a single story of a community glad to have them i think we should sit and think on that
thank you mr dastran how you doing wonderful tony dash at 700 block of new holland avenue i will do my best to keep this one positive uh because i'm very glad to see this ordinance director delfs it is way more robust than i honestly had been anticipating so i appreciate the reviews you've done of all the documentation you've been provided by the public um i do have some notes and i also want to thank you for your calling out of the good faith that was one of the things i underlined as soon as i read this um so moving on from the good faith that will definitely come up later in other agenda items but i want to encourage the council to change it from special exception to conditional use especially in light of not having an updated zoning amendment right now this is working in between where we need to get with our comprehensive plan and what where we're at right now so I think the most acceptable thing for the public would to be having conditional uses because as these data centers move through our community it holds this body directly accountable to what products are approved in addition of that I believe under electronic waste mr. Arcolio has persuaded me that we need to have a bond to guarantee that those plans get enacted and that should be outlined explicitly in those electronic waste plans with a bond as far as water utilization goes I do believe there's a way for us to draft agnostic legislation because industrial use of water not just for data centers but other facilities is something that is a very real impact for our community potable water where it's available especially in a community a a community like ours that is dependent on rainfall to dilute the, what are we calling them, PFAS in our water, it's critical that we save every drop of potable water we have. So they shouldn't be going to just cooling uses. If something's not producing a consumable product by humans, animals, or otherwise agricultural use, I think we need to eliminate that. Yeah, I mean, honestly, this is a nice big packet. I'm very happy to see the direction we're heading in as far as the legislation goes obviously we as a community have more work to do when it comes to these existing data centers i'm looking forward to seeing uh the review by planning commission which for the record i am on um because we are a little bit behind on where we need to be with this uh the fact that we are in this place we should have never gotten to this place um so those are the changes i would recommend making to uh this ordinance i will obviously say those things at planning commission as well i appreciate the public for continuing in this fight uh to protect our honestly not just our well-being but our ecosystem for uh generations to come and thank you please move this forward so we can get something in place
thank you mr dastra um there you go you knew i'd be up here frank garcolio uh old trinity place uh yeah so uh i have to say that this is a lot better than i expected um and i recognize a lot of the language in here like some of the definitions and and things like that that look very similar to uh to what i uh handed out at the last city council meeting uh there are there are some things that are missing um i think uh things about grid costs uh energy energy management plan has been uh the fact that it is that that ppl will not give information about any energy agreements that it has with customers i think we need we would definitely need to require that the uh the applicants provide their uh energy use plan um i think there's uh some stuff that is missing here there's not a decommissioning plan there's a lot of uh a lot of talk in uh in the financial circles that we are in a large data center bubble and that that bubble could burst at any time uh and uh and so it is possible that at the first turnaround when the first set of uh of chips become obsolete that all of a sudden that data center completely refurbished with new chips will not be able to compete and will be decommissioned i would hate to see them just walking away and throwing the keys on the roof we need a decommissioning plan and as mr dastra said for all of these plans the energy management plan the water utilization plan the electronic waste plan the heat mitigation plan all of these things should be accompanied by a performance bond so that if they don't meet the terms that they uh that they have uh that they have said that uh there are not only legal remedies but also financial penalties uh that we can that we can extract um you know i i i guess probably the longest term thing is the energy problem um and and you know what i think familiarizing yourself with the date with data centers in order to draft this ordinance was a great thing i just believe that it should have been done way before the first set was ever uh agreed to by the city and that um and that i still believe that my appeal will be successful because if you look at the definitions and you look at uh the the the differences between uh warehouses and what's been defined here YOU WILL SEE THAT THEY ARE NOT THE SAME THERE'S NO WAY TO CONFUSE THEM AND THERE NEVER SHOULD HAVE BEEN ANYTHING AT ALL APPROVING THOSE THINGS WITHOUT THIS KIND OF WORK AHEAD OF TIME AND THIS KIND OF PROCESS THAT TAKES IT THROUGH BOTH A MULTI-STEP OFFICIAL PROCESS AS WELL AS A PUBLIC comment process so uh i think this is a great first step um i think i think we can improve on it and uh and good luck i hope thank you thank you hello my name is jacob dadisman a recent resident
over on king and lime street i i just have a couple questions um i would like to see uh how the zoning rules would be regulated um and additionally uh what kind of consequences there will be for these corporations who are establishing these centers in our community right now i haven't been to any of the earlier meetings but right now i'm looking at a few pages with a lot of vague wording no metrics and no accountability and that really concerns me i moved all the way across the country with my wife we want to start a new life here and we don't want want to see it destroyed for a few dozen jobs so if we could revise it a little bit and get some hard numbers get some facts get some figures from the other data centers like the other gentleman said they're affecting other cities and states across America with these giant data centers the health the environment that would be greatly appreciated and I'm very happy to be before you and allowed to give public comment and we would love to see that continue thank
thank you thank you like set up from back there but uh my name is taylor enterline i'm a community organizer with lancaster stands up i'm from the manheim borough can you hear me now better um my name is taylor enterline i'm a community organizer with lancaster stands up i'm part of manheim borough though i just wanted to really thank council and y'all's two time for taking the time to write this um ordinance it's very important my favorite part is in terms of the need for community input especially for the community taxing and costs that will be on our folks here and wanting to point out of the fact that one individual went behind the backs of many people to sell out our community for big tech and now we have to go through all this to make sure that amendments are made so my hope is that once we get the answers if this would be RETROACTIVE AND AROUND THE COMMUNITY BENEFITS AGREEMENT, HOPING THAT THERE'S AN OPEN FORUM FOR OUR FOLKS TO ACTUALLY HAVE INPUT ON THAT BEFORE ANY DECISIONS ARE MADE ARE REALLY IMPORTANT. THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME.
THANK YOU. ALL RIGHT.
TAYLOR RAYMOND, 500 BLOCK OF ST. JOSEPH STREET. I AGREE WITH EVERYONE WHO'S SPOKEN PREVIOUSLY, THEY ARE A LOT MORE ELOQUENT AND SMARTER THAN ME IN REGARDS TO THE DATA Center I have a couple of questions so if a if a plan is approved and the data center is developed and then what they submitted doesn't or what they do doesn't live up to what they submitted it doesn't meet the requirements what consequences do they suffer under this current zoning ordinance or under the proposed one and then additionally about the community benefits agreement so I looked up just a basic definition of what that was just to make sure I knew what I was talking about and it says that it is a contract signed by community groups and a real estate developer so I wanted to know what community groups are involved in that um because i don't i don't know of any and i would love to know if there are any um that are being included thank you can i get some answers on those um
we're not going to do question and answer right at this moment i will after meeting or you can submit your question to the clerk and we'll get it answered council craig sure i would just endeavor
to try to answer that uh dr delves he said that we're very early in that process for community benefit so i don't know that we have that just yet that we're at that point but it's well taken so thank you um and the first question i cannot remember it at this point but i wanted to say
something about it and now i can't remember um it was the what consequences would they suffer
if they thank you thank you i shared that question so director dallas if you could just speak generally about how zoning ordinances are enforced that may be helpful in the context of this
question thank you uh sure very quickly on the community benefits thank you we're planning to speak about that uh later in the month so i do think it'd be premature to talk about that now i do appreciate the question um i i'll let uh betsy answer the question about uh the zoning
enforcement just in general yeah just in general because this is uncharted territory yes indeed
thank you thank you so zoning enforcement is already written in the zoning ordinance it's a set procedure the zoning officer if there is an enforcement issue a complaint or a violation he would investigate that complaint and he would file a notice of violation that would go through the process that can be appealed to the zoning hearing board the notice of violation can or at who can make changes to any approvals they have they can uphold it they can deny it but it would
go through the zoning hearing board so the same process that any zoning violations would generally
yes they can if they don't address the the concern or the issue after a notice of a violation is sent in um and no action has been taken we can file with the district magistrate on those um i would foresee that probably not happening with this it doesn't happen frequently but it
is recourse that's available to us okay thank you okay upon seeing no one else up at the mic
hello my name is sophia pangburn i'm from the 200s block of king street and i just want to 100 clarify just to make sure that i understand this correctly that even if this zoning uh thing is passed it doesn't necessarily apply to the two warehouses that are currently already
uh being proposed and built correct uh right so what what i was hoping we could do uh tonight uh and in the process we we have to think about this zoning amendment as applying to the entire city i do understand uh that there's a key question related to uh there's the east campus proposed at greenfield road and the west campus uh proposed at harrisburg pike and as i said earlier the city does not have a legal position at this point about whether it would apply to uh to either of those sites because of the progress that the greenfield road site has made through the building permit process for example on phase one the developer is more legally safe with the fact that they proceeded with with that work if you understand me but it's it is not a black-and-white answer okay so that so that's why I'm saying that there has been no determination yet for certain about whether this zoning amendment
would apply to those two sites okay so this all of this has been complete hypotheticals and there's just absolutely no guarantee that there will be any kind of precautions for noise for environmental safety for electricity for responsibility in any kind of way like there's absolutely no recourse or rules that these warehouses have to follow um if this does not apply to them in the future that's not how the
city's approaching it no okay thank you is anybody else gonna sneak up to the mic okay thank you upon seeing no one else at the mic i'm going to make oh first of all let me make a clarification because i think in the very beginning that i referred to this as council bill 5 and it's council bill 10 okay and then now i would like to make a motion to move council bill 10 to full council on the 14th okay all those in favor well second second thank you and then all those in favor all right all right thank you council president that concludes community planning for this evening thank you very much director Delph and
and your team thank you very much for that we look forward to continued conversation about it we'll now move to the Public Safety Committee councillor
Diaz Thank You president Public Safety Committee has administration bill number AUTHORIZING AUTOMATED RED LIGHT ENFORCEMENT. THIS ORDINANCE AUTHORIZES THE CITY OF LANCASTER TO IMPLEMENT AND ENFORCE AUTOMATED RED LIGHT CAMERA IN DESIGNATED INTERSECTIONS IN ACCORDING TO PENNSYLVANIA LAW. I WILL LET OUR WONDERFUL REPRESENTATIVE HERE TO DISCUSS THAT.
THANK YOU, COUNCILOR DIAZ. I'M FROM THE DEPARTMENT OF FROM THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS. WE'VE BEEN WORKING CLOSELY WITH THE POLICE DEPARTMENT ON THE AUTOMATED RED LIGHT RUNNING LEGISLATOR PROGRAM. AND I'LL BE HERE TO PRESENT A LITTLE BIT MORE INFORMATION ABOUT IT. SO AS YOU MENTIONED, THIS IS A REQUEST FOR AN ORDINANCE AUTHORIZING THE ENFORCEMENT OF RED LIGHT RUNNING CAMERAS THROUGH AN AUTOMATED SYSTEM. THE SYSTEM WOULD ALSO BE APPROVED BY PEN DOT SO JUST FOR PEOPLE THAT AREN'T FAMILIAR WITH AUTOMATED RED LIGHT RUNNING CAMERAS THERE ARE CAMERAS THAT ARE LOCATED AT TRAFFIC SIGNALS AND THEY RECORD RED LIGHT RUNNING VIOLATIONS POLICE THEN REVIEW THESE PHOTOS TO CONFIRM VIOLATIONS AND THEN THEY THEY APPROVE THE CITATIONS THAT ARE ISSUED AND THEN TICKETS ARE MAILED TO THE REGISTERED vehicle owners as part of the program so why are we looking at automated red light running enforcement as you're all aware we're very heavily invested in traffic safety throughout the city our vision zero plan has a focus on eliminating fatal and serious injury crashes so this is a another tool for us to use in deterring speeding and other behaviors that lead to crashes just to give a little bit more background in 2025 there were 25 seriously injured or killed people in the city of lancaster we have over 700 crashes per year approximately half of those involve some form of injury and we have 35 to 40 crashes generally during the year that involve pedestrians so we're looking to implement as many tools as we can to improve safety in the city with the accreditation of the police department recently that allowed us to move forward with this program and the goals of the program are to reduce the red light running violations a lot of studies have shown once these cameras are implemented the actual number of violations go down over time so that's obviously what we're trying to curb that red light running behavior it reduces angle crashes angle crashes often result in higher degrees of injuries so studies have shown that some red light running cameras will reduce all injury crashes by approximately 20 percent and up to 30 percent for right angle crashes so this is has been proven to be effective in reducing crashes it also has been known to have a spillover effect so this ordinance is requesting installation of cameras at five intersections within the city but once a program has been implemented often there is a reduction in red light running in general throughout the area so the locations in THIS ORDINANCE ARE LISTED ON THE SECOND PAGE OF THE ORDINANCE BUT THEY INCLUDE KING STREET AND LIME KING AND WATER COLUMBIA AVENUE AND WEST END AVENUE LIME AND WALNUT AND THEN MANOR HERSHEY AND WEST END AND THESE LOCATIONS WERE SELECTED BASED ON THE HIGHEST NUMBER OF CRASHES CONTRIBUTED TO RED LIGHT RUNNING WE ALSO TRIED TO DISPERSED THEM THROUGHOUT THE CITY SO NOT focusing on any one particular area and then we've also had some initial coordination with pendot who has to approve the locations that we choose as well so just to provide a little bit more information the program would include and a lot of the details of the program are listed out in the ordinance but the program does include you know required education and signage associated WITH THE CAMERAS AND ALSO INCLUDES A 60 DAY INITIAL PERIOD WHERE VIOLATIONS ARE NOT ISSUED IT'S MORE WARNINGS SO THERE'S PLENTY OF PUBLIC NOTICE ABOUT THE PROGRAM THE TICKETS WILL BE CIVIL OFFENSES THEY ARE NOT CONSIDERED CRIMINAL THEY DO NOT ADD POINTS TO ANYONE'S RECORD THE CITY WILL HAVE TO SET UP SINCE IT IS A CIVIL CIVIL VIOLATION. THE CITY WILL HAVE TO SET UP AN APPEAL PROCESS FOR THOSE CIVIL VIOLATIONS, BUT THAT IS PART OF WHAT WE PLAN TO DO. AND THE SYSTEM WILL NOT GENERATE ANY REVENUE FOR THE CITY. FINES ARE COLLECTED AND THE CITY IS REIMBURSED FOR THEIR EXPENSES RELATED TO THE POLICE TIME AS WELL AS THE VENDOR IS REIMBURSED FOR THOSE EXPENSES. ANY ADDITIONAL REVENUE OVER THAT WOULD GO BACK TO THE STATE. A LOT OF THIS FUNDING THAT GOES BACK TO THE STATE IS USED FOR AUTOMATED RED LIGHT ENFORCEMENT GRANTS, WHICH THE CITY IS OFTEN A RECIPIENT OF AS WELL. SO THE CITY WOULD NOT BE ABLE TO MAKE ANY REVENUE RELATED TO THIS PROGRAM. AND WE'RE ALSO REQUIRED, IF THIS PROGRAM IS IMPLEMENTED, WE WOULD IMPLEMENTED, WE WOULD BE REQUIRED TO DO ANNUAL REPORTS NOTING THE NUMBER OF VIOLATIONS AND DETAILING OUT REVENUE AND EXPENSES RELATED TO THE PROGRAM. SO IF THIS IS APPROVED, THE NEXT STEPS WOULD BE TO MAKE A FORMAL REQUEST, AND THEN BECAUSE THIS HAS TO BE APPROVED BY THE SECRETARY OF TRANSPORTATION, AND THEN WE WOULD ISSUE AN RFP FOR VENDORS.
IS THERE ANY QUESTIONS FROM THE COMMITTEE?
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THE PRESENTATION. MY QUESTION IS, WILL THIS ALSO CAPTURE SOMEONE THAT WOULD ILLEGALLY TURN RIGHT IN A NO TURN ON RED SITUATION?
YES, WE CAN SET IT UP SO THAT IT WILL SELECT THOSE VIOLATIONS AS WELL. VERY GOOD.
AND I JUST WANT TO MAKE A COMMENT IN SUPPORT OF THIS BECAUSE I WITNESS IT EVERY DAY, PEOPLE RUNNING RED LIGHTS. IT'S INCREDIBLY DANGEROUS. I HAD A DEAR FRIEND WHO WAS HIT, SEVERELY INJURED BOTH PHYSICALLY AND EMOTIONALLY, MENTALLY, AND I'M JUST REALLY GLAD TO SEE THE CITY PURSUE THIS IN OUR NEST BECAUSE I THINK IT'S LONG OVERDUE. THANK YOU. ANY OTHER QUESTIONS FROM
COUNCIL? YES.
THANK YOU, COUNCILOR DIAZ. MS. MCCORMICK, THANK YOU SO MUCH. THIS IS VERY EXCITING. and i would echo council herch's comments and support i also just want to put a fine point on the fact that because this will be the headline right this is the city is trying to make money so to confirm we cannot make any money off of this program because after we are reimbursed for our time and we pay for the technology it goes to the state of pennsylvania is that correct absolutely
CORRECT THANK YOU SO MUCH AND UM I'LL OPEN UP TO UM TO ANY COMMENTS BECAUSE I'M SURE THAT THE PUBLIC MIGHT WANT TO MAKE A COMMENT ABOUT THIS CASCALOPEZ LANCASTER PRESIDENT I GUESS THIS IS ONE
UM WHERE I'M NOT YOU KNOW PRO HELPING THE POLICE UM I DO BELIEVE WE HAVE AN ENORMOUS AMOUNT OF HIT runs in this city that do not get solved so um yes where safety is concerned we do need new measures but we shouldn't be relying on trapping our residents to make money um i get that our city needs to find ways to pay for it but it shouldn't be coming from trapping our residents no matter what that looks like if that is paying attention to if they turned right on red um we pay out our wazoos to live in lancaster as it stands right now with the way our cost of living is and where i like i said i do believe we need to do something because safety is prevalent um i also know somebody that was in a hit and run um at the beginning of this year and they suffered immensely so yes we do need to do something but i don't believe that we should be searching for ways to entrap people to fix our financial issues i know but that was the statement that was made about whether we were going to make any money off of this and no we're not where it needs to happen it shouldn't be about if we're going to make money off of it it should be about if our residents are
going to be safe or not to clarify miss lopez the reason i asked that question was because i wanted to make sure it was clear that we didn't because that's not my wish either i'm like nope we we
i don't think we should do that either like we pay out the wazoo and parking tickets we're paying out the wazoo and housing costs i just think that where we do need safer solutions like something on manor and philbert that decreases the speed because i just almost watched a kid get hit by a car two days ago but we don't have a light there we do need different things implemented i just think it should be fiscally better for our residents all right uh hi my name's uh nikolai
skycus i'm a resident on 300 west lemon that block um there's there definitely are studies that don't necessarily show it improves safety um i was looking at one right here before uh i didn't didn't know this was on the agenda uh and so i uh i can provide that for anyone who wants uh it essentially was a study in houston saying they stopped the red light cameras and they said well we're not totally sure whether or not it improved safety or not and slam on the brakes when they were like you know just about to uh like blow it i'm saying like much earlier creating you know dangerous incidents i've been in the car in front or you know behind those people who have been in those situations. I don't necessarily believe that this will improve safety. I think it might just change the accidents that we're seeing here in Lancaster. I would also just say that anecdotally from, well, from where, you know, I grew up, I'm very happy to be living in Lancaster, but in the Chicagoland area, there's a lot of bureaucracy in fighting tickets and Google shirts can show that there have even been instances with these red light camera companies i'm not sure if it'll be the same one servicing the city but in getting completely wrong license plates uh of people who they said oh this is your car and it actually wasn't their car it was someone else's car and there was no way to uh to fight it people had a hard time doing that so i would just if this was going to go into place i would make sure that there would be a robust system for people to fight the tickets uh so that they didn't get wrongfully ticketed because you know they are pricey um and i would echo the previous commenters uh the speaker's thoughts about other ideas for safer streets like you know you can narrow the streets i i'm just saying there's other ideas too that we don't necessarily need to resort to just red light cameras to slow down people so please do not pass
this good evening my name is john allison 400 block of west lemon streets um my largest concern is going to be the administrative burden that is placed upon the residents of lancaster just seeing if there is a false signal or something like that how the appeals process is going to go it's an automated system so it's basically placing the majority of that administrative burden on lancaster uh residents as well as i was looking at the proposal i saw it cost about a hundred thousand dollars per traffic light and i'm just wondering if this is the best use of funds compared to having other public safety measures throughout lancaster um one of the things i've seen a lot of times while i'm driving around the city is not is the motorized bicycles or the uh different types of scooters that people uh ride around very fast and i've there's been numerous accidents here in the city where people have been where they run red lights none of those vehicles are required to have license plates or have any ability to be fined because they're more like a bicycle than they are a commuting traffic like a commuter car or a motorcycle when i see that they are as much of a danger or in as much a danger as a motorcycle going with within the speed limits on city property or like it within the city limits so those are my two things that i think is just if we're looking at this potential uh administrative burden. And then I'm just wondering if that's going to actually stop people going through the red lights. I know in the early mornings, a lot of people go through, especially down like Prince Street, and they'll use the progressive green lights to start almost preemptively going through the red lights. I know that can cause accidents. So I just wanted to know what that is. And then also the time difference between someone, let's say they enter a yellow light, when does that red light cameras start taking effect like are they if they're halfway through the intersection when it turns red because of some of these traffic signals are very very fast so I just want to know what when people are going to be get penalized and if so do we know any more additional information
on that thank you thank you is that something that you could answer yeah I mean related to
when they would be fine I mean they have to they would enter have to enter the intersection so if you're at an intersection waiting to make a left turn lane and you're in the intersection and it turns red while you're in that would not count it has to be your once you you're entering the intersection after the light has turned red so if you're in the intersection during any part of the yellow phase you would not be gotcha have a violation thank you and one
Some other question I'd ask is, could we also possibly spend better money by installing more opticons on the streetlights for emergency response vehicles? I know that a lot of the streets of the city, especially around the hospital, where there are a lot of emergency response vehicles, they don't have the ability to have opticons or areas where those could be actually very well implemented compared to installing these red light street cameras. So instead of having emergency vehicles cutting across traffic on a green light, instead of
making it a red light thank you tony dastro 700 block of new holland avenue uh whenever i see this sort of legislation i do get a little bit weirded out because like you know uber driver so i've seen plenty of other uber drivers and i know how it is when uh enforcement picks up but i do think it's a good thing i do think that these sort of enforcements are necessary for our community i kind of joke about the whole uber driver deal but uh no i've driven philly for a summer and the red light cameras work there, the speed cameras work there, and I certainly was watching my behavior in streets I wasn't familiar with when I saw photo enforcement. But I want to encourage you on one change. I believe it said that there's like, you know, civil penalties for these. I would encourage city council to amend it to include that the court may at their discretion designate these penalties can be paid by community service. There's other ordinances that allow for that not traffic but I do think this is applicable here because it's a civil offense and I think it makes sense because the city every year we do bike counts and if people are running red lights and they do end up happen to getting offense it could provide an opportunity for the city to source volunteer labor to help with these traffic counts in the future so and also if somebody can't really afford the hundred dollars but they learn their lesson you know it provides an opportunity there as well so there's a real benefit to amending this to include diverse ways of pay I've always called it fines of time and that's what I've encouraged the council on thank you
but Nathan Charles hopefully for 400 block of West Lemon so I had a question so who is responsible for the the enforcement of these cameras enforcement
I mean the police are the ones that would actually issue the ticket yeah but
But in terms of the operation, so there was the observation that potentially we could add additional function for enforcement, like turning a right on a red.
That's still running a red light, I guess. So that's what would be covered.
So the question is, could the, what these cameras ticket be changed in the future? only with legislative changes for at the state level okay now the this in chicago they changed the timing of yellow lights they shortened the yellow lights to increase um the by a tenth of a second is is there any chance that that would happen here no i would say there's something in
the ordinance i was just reading that says that we can't deviate from the standard set by the
by pen dot okay um appreciate it because i've i've been hit twice in a crosswalk walking on green so i definitely uh in very um want to see more safety in crosswalks but at the same time you know i've heard some good good comments here don't want to make sure that we're exacerbating
any problems um so anyway thanks all right quickly i just uh susie hoover um i was out of state for an event with the family and my hostess who was older had me drive and as i drove through the city and i did not know this she said drive faster and i said no but the speed limit says this she said don't worry when i got home i did have two photographs of my car speeding with this type of system i didn't go through a red light it was actually on the street and i went there was my license plate there was the camera clearly it was me so i actually got points out of it i almost thought about writing my uh writing my hostess but she was such a cool lady i thought i wouldn't and i just paid it but this system does work it does work thank you and just to reiterate this is not
speed enforcement that is precluded by state law we are not allowed to use cameras for speed import enforcement there is only one place that cameras are allowed for speed enforcement and that is
philadelphia yep if there's no other comments i would like to go ahead and move this to full council on october 14th second all in favor aye thank you very much and the next one is a council bill um 05 2025 creating community police review board um i think this has been hanging for what three or four months now nobody's responding um the bill was sent i've met with the mayor and several police officers they were in the panel and the response was that it was illegal and just to make it clear it's not illegal because pittsburgh has a beautiful um website that has a citizens police review board so anybody that wants to take a look at that you're welcome to see it they have the meetings there um and i'm just gonna basically say it you know i'm going to bring it forward because as i told them i'm here to support the community this is what the community wanted and this is my job whether they vote for it i doubt it very highly but at least you know that i did my job okay so if there's any questions from council go ahead um i'm i can you can you've already had the bill for what a month and a half now um and if not i'll open up to the public if they want to make comments on it counselor diaz if i may go ahead from the
public safety committee my questions were was there any legal review of this resolution when
it was written well if you heard the mayor and she told me that it was illegal it was very interesting that if if a different state i mean a different county has it it's obviously not illegal and if you look at it and you read it there's nothing there that's going to show that there's going to be any voting power whatsoever it's just to have a community people and it's going to include police officers even though i know for sure that some people in the community feel that that's not really the reason to have it it's more for the for you to say look this person broke the law this person was aggressive this person you know did not follow the law um but this is very simple i mean even city council is going to be appointing um the even police officers is going to be on their social worker and community members it's not any type of voting power whatsoever thank you and my question was when it was written was there
any legal review not when you met with the administration but when the resolution was
WRITTEN WAS THERE ANY LEGAL REVIEW I WOULD HAVE TO GO BACK AND LOOK AT MY EMAILS BECAUSE THIS HAS
BEEN A WHILE AND THAT GOES TO MY SECOND POINT YOU KNOW UM WITH THE CURRENT COLLECTIVE BARGAIN AGREEMENT WAS THERE ANY THOUGHT INTO HOW SOME TYPE OF APPARATUS SUCH AS A PUBLIC SAFETY COMMISSION REVIEW BOARD UM WHATEVER IT MAY BE HOW THAT WORKS WITH OUR CURRENT COMMUNITY UH WELL WITH OUR CURRENT UH AGREEMENT WITH THE I CAN SEND YOU THAT INFORMATION I DON'T I JUST DON'T HAVE IT
unfortunately i have a fever so i'm a little bit out of it today but um i will i can forward that to everyone in city council and if you have a question tony go ahead well i'm not i'm not
finished oh you're not finished and and lastly i would just you know like to note that you know without any robust input from the solicitor's office from the chief of police and given that we're going to have a new chief of police a new administration and a new public safety commission um i don't think this resolution is appropriate and that's my final comment i would also like
to i guess ask the question if like if the administration's position is that it's not legal i would want to know what the what the reasoning or like um you know i i if if that was if that was said that i would want to know you know what the what the reasoning behind that is was there any discussion about um like like whether this constitutes mandated participation without compensation on the behalf of the officers because that would violate the collective bargaining agreement um you know i think there's a lot of folks that have really uh pushed for this that told me when they saw this that it wasn't to their liking and i think it goes back to the original point that mayor sirachi made in march which is that i think the unfortunate reality is that this would create a misalignment of expectations did you discuss what review or what evidence would be admissible to such a board like i said before i'd have to forward that
information to you because i have it all written down and i would be happy to okay and i also will send you the citizen police review board from pittsburgh i don't have any other questions i
definitely do not feel comfortable with this given all of those concerns and not getting
an answer counselor diaz may ask a question i'm just yeah i'm just curious i feel like we jumped right into this but typically with ordinances i know we do a review of the process and also the highlights of the ordinance would you mind presenting the ordinance and talking to us a little bit about your process in drafting this ordinance did you draft it did the solicitor draft it kind of curious about i'm going to go ahead and i worked pardon me i worked with tony
in regards to this and i also was working with um some of the pittsburgh people that i know up there who are the pittsburgh people city council i'll forward that information as well looking forward
to it thank you so i've put most of this together council diaz may i address before we take public
comment thank you um i i had ample opportunity to review this because i think this has come up for three months now and i have some lingering questions um most notably about the participation of the police social worker that's proposed here as an employee of the police department i would I would be very concerned about having another employee have access to personnel records. That seems to me a pretty distinct violation. I think that it, that just speaks to the nature of this particular bill being written without any sort of regard or legal review. It seems like from an employment law perspective, that that seems pretty basic. Is there, did anyone look at this an employment law perspective when it was drafted that i did not go through but i can thank you
the mic is open okay tony dash 700 block of new holland avenue yeah so most of what you're seeing before you uh was put together by myself sent them as diaz for her review uh and no i did not have a lawyer look over it prior um this is one of those rare examples where a community member puts together an ordinance and then gives it to council and action can or cannot be taken frankly the most upsetting thing for me over these last three months is to see the lack of action here i said these words would circle back good faith faith without works is dead and we as the public have not observed the work taking place to get these sort of initiatives done yes we have the citizens police academy which I've signed myself up to participate in I think that has a place in these sort of discussions but it's not a replacement for these sort of mechanisms yes this is not disciplinary but while I did not get legal review I did read the union contract the point that I think is most valid to make here mr. Hirsch said compensation if you're going to be on this board and you're a member of the police force the reason there are, frankly, more positions than just the chief listed there, because I would suspect that the chief would be compensated as it would become a necessary part of their function to participate. I think that's a valid question to ask. And frankly, I would be comfortable not having those other police members on, but I included them in my draft because I thought it gave a diversity of perspectives, not just the executive function of the police department. So that's why those other police members are there. And if we wanted to replace them with community members that's fine but the reason why I think it's necessary for y'all to move this forward not to approve it as is to continue having these discussions in public where we can call the police to present their position where we can get legal review on these matters so we can answer these questions because we need some change on this issue we need some change on this issue and we need to move this forward to continue the conversations because otherwise I personally will acknowledge for the rest of my life that this moment occurred and there was no desire to continue the conversation because regardless of a new mayor regardless of a new police chief y'all are the city council and you are responsible for drafting the legislation for which the mayor has to enforce and the police have to follow this is the place and time to have these conversations especially when we're about to undergo change so that's what have to say i think your questions and miss diaz are valid um but the public deserves those answers as well we need to continue this as an open process that's how we build transparency and
trust in our police thank you jessica lopez lancaster city resident and thank god we're finally at this point um i want to say that it's kind of disappointing where i can't stand all the way with this resolution i feel like it's very disappointing that jews aren't taking this serious that youse aren't doing the background search since march 2nd to find a way to quell the distrust between city council our police department and our city residents the fact that tony had to create some type of proposal and then get the one most pro-police city council member we have to put this forward says a lot um i think that being i can't stand with it being that our city solicitor just signed on with our district attorney to try to silence the transparency in the march 2nd video incident that we're still fighting for we can't trust that our city is here to protect us they are literally meeting november 4th on election day to decide whether these body cam footages are allowed or not who's going to be in that courtroom that's sitting up here that vowed to protect us i would hope that you know the protection of our children would be more important than elections and stuff and when that court proceeding goes on november 4th somebody from city council will be there because these are very important decisions that are being made no this police working group as it stands right now i cannot stand with i can't agree with we do need an authoritative stance from our community to our police department we do need a voice at the table when that collective bargaining agreement is being revisited coming up we do need a say in our own protection because every response that came from you guys to this proposal is if the police were going to be protected in this and not if the community was actually going to be protected we asked if a social worker being involved is going to release police information what about the protection of our residents that's what we're asking for it might not look like this police working group that was proposed to you but it does look like the the ass for the last eight months since that bike incident transpired outside all we're asking for is for you to really do what you said jews would do when you ran to get up here like that's sad i mean there's times i've come up and spoken for you there's times i've come up and spoken on behalf of a lot of things that people are proposing up here and yet again every day you sit in these seats and do not speak for us but we're worried about the protection of our police officers yes there is a working group in pittsburgh that oversees their police department there's also a court watch set up in pittsburgh pittsburgh does a lot to protect their residents not just capitalize on them lancaster literally sat here for hours pushed this to the very end and then acted like our ass are wrong no we need protection and we put y'all in place to do it so if we need lawyers to review and figure out how we can legally get a resident review board of our police department that's y'all job that's not tony's job that's not this community's job that's your guys's job to figure out how to protect the people that put you in place so yes we do need a police working group it's not the one that is put in this proposal that this does need table though it doesn't need revisited and you need to do your job to make it so that this resolution fits our
community that's it thank you well it looks like um we can go ahead and table it while i forward all the information to you and i'll also send you the draft that pittsburgh has um that can be looked at as well and i'll send it to the solicitor go ahead hi my name is taylor taylor
enterline uh community organizer with lancaster stands up part of manhattan borough um i do appreciate tony taking the time to bring this and funnel it through janet i do think though I don't see how it's different from what came out of 2020 and that has dissolved and our community has asked for more something with teeth and so I would ask that like regardless if you know the conversation the conversation cannot stop here so what you vote on this but that each of you would take the time to work with folks whether that's community organizers community folks if it is the police to figure out what the solution here is because something does need to give I mean we are going to get a new chief we are going to get a new mayor and I hope that those folks are willing to like work with the community we are told all the time to come to the table continuously we do and so I hope that something is on the table for us to actually have some power here when we talk about our police and how our folks are policed here in the city thank you I'll make a motion to
table bill number five could you specify until when and I'm I'm want to be clear about this because I do think that there is some community conversation that council should have and some other conversation and I would look to councillor Diaz to lead that I think Taylor's point miss enter lines point is well taken you're asking for something with teeth and I am suggesting that there are many legal barriers to that at the state and some at the local level that are not even addressed by what Pittsburgh has and so I find myself in this conversation again and again since 2017 in trying to respond to the request from the community to respond with something with accountability with something with teeth show me another community in Pennsylvania that has a
citizen police review board with teeth show me I think to answer that question there's another one that Harrisburg has which I still have to look at that again i don't i i believe that the mayor hasn't appointed her staff according to the conversation i have with one of the city council members but um yeah we just have to continue speaking to the community and we have to look at what we can draw up but i mean we continue i mean the only thing that's going to happen is another incident's going to occur where something's going to be even worse and they're going to come back here again they're going to tell you i want something now and how
many months later or how many years later you know counselor diaz maybe it's because i'm nearing the end of my term but i just want to say that when you came to the meeting the police chief was at the head of the table you were sitting to his left i was sitting across from you we were joined by six or eight police officers and your point of view was that you repeated what you said earlier tonight that you were at this meeting to represent um the community you did not make a case for the ordinance you simply stated that this was you were there because the community wanted you there and you don't have any problems with the police so i take great great umbrage at the way that you are presenting yourself tonight as some champion of the community on this issue thank you i would
like to close them i mean i there was a table there we had a motion to table i did not hear
a second um this is your committee but it was the parliamentarian advice i would i mean if we're
making a motion to to table um you know i i i i i will state again that i do not support this for the reasons that were aforementioned that it creates a misalignment between the community's expectations and reality and that that's kind of the issue at hand and that's that's that's kind of emblematic to me of the conversations i've been having of people who saw this and said well i don't like that there's three police officers on it and i don't like that it doesn't have teeth and there is no such you know as the mayor stated there's not there's no example of that in pennsylvania so i i i don't support it and i'm i like i'm tabling it as in like i'm done with the conversation um and if that means we have to table it until january 2026 that's my motion
a second so to be clear because my question with the tabling is you know when are we tabling this till you know what steps are going to be taken by the chair of this committee uh in that time um and i i don't want us to continue to keep coming to this conversation about the same root flawed issues within this proposal if we want to give the new administration and the new police chief time to work this out and report back in january i i think that's something that the public safety committee at that time could request but tabling this until next year i i i don't feel is appropriate and that does not mean that we can't continue to have community conversations with you know folks with community groups but but simply tabling the same flawed document is is not going to result in any change that the public is looking for nor would be
be productive for this body well if anything i can table it till the 28th so i can get all the information out and get more people on the on at the table unless there's a problem which is fine
i'm here for the people the 28th would be our second meeting in october and i don't mr harris i believe we would need this to come through committee as a bill yes so if the very the earliest would be our committee meeting in november which would be november 3rd if that's
the intent um yes ma'am um i just i wanted to respond um to everyone in the mayor specifically is i don't think i i think you're right like we can look at other places in pa and try and see what we can resemble i don't think what what i'm saying is i don't think we should recreate what came out of 2020 and died and nothing came out of it but i think is like we should there should be a conversation of what we can like move forward i know we're not going to get every little thing in terms of what it is with teeth i know in terms of the state level in terms of here locally in terms of like dealing with the da's office but i do think there are ways that we can work together to get something that is more substantial than what was proposed and that there's a conversation that can continue to be had outside of what is proposed as well i i don't know the exact date um in terms of when the next bargaining uh like contract goes in or um what those conversations need to be had even before you know a new administration comes in or before a new chief comes in like I think groundwork can continue to be laid outside of what is proposed and I would hope that we don't table till indefinitely that there's conversations that are still happening outside of what
is in front of you that's what I would ask and I would just say that as I come to the conclusion of my term and there is an effort that's currently getting started to hire a new police chief that it would really be premature to i think it would be in the community's best interest to engage the new mayor and the police chief in these conversations in order to be able to have the kind of robust conversation that's necessary and i think that that is part of an expectation of hiring a new chief is engaging in the community to talk about ways to continue to build trust and rapport i would like for that chief to have that opportunity and so my recommendation is like just set this down i don't really trust where this is all going just me personally as a city resident set it down have the opportunity to engage in these conversations be clear about expectations around community engagement involvement if you're not happy about the way that the community working group fell apart there just wasn't any participation and so there and and that is a challenge and so it it did it fell it did fall apart and some other really good things were born out of that that we're working on now with the school district and pccd around youth gun violence and things like that so it's not like nothing happened and you know I also just want to take note you know I was I did not have a great relationship with the police department and did not have a lot of confidence in them early in my tenure and that has changed for me and I think it can continue to change for this community as well we have come so far since 2020 in the work that this community has done together with our police bureau and i am really proud of that work and i want to see it continue and i think that these kinds of conversations get muddled in the expectations being set beyond what can actually be delivered so you know i just i think also to counsel you have a budget to pass you have a home rule administrative code to pass you've got a zoning text amendment and whatever else we are going to throw at you between now and the end of the year and there are 10 meetings left so i just want to be realistic in a holiday season through all of the work that's ahead is this really going to become the priority before the end of this and before we can name a new police chief just being
real i would just quickly respond in terms of i 100 hear what you're saying and not saying that anything didn't come out of it i hear what you're saying in terms of what is happening between the end of the year i just don't think the conversation should die and i think that there could be conversations and steps taken before the new chief comes in to engage with him and or him or them or her in that way and that's all i'll have to say thank you citizen tony daschle 700 block new
holland avenue citizens police oversight commission out in philadelphia appears to have some teeth to it um the commission works to increase the transparency they're a class one city mr dastra they operate under different rules yeah and we also need to get police accreditation to get red light cameras there are certain mechanisms so i guess what i'm really trying to make the point of is that you asked for another municipality i gave you one what we as the public need is education on this perspective this goes all the way back to other issues we should have like if we're going to work on this you wanted reports from the police right on this issue let's let's lay it out on paper like here's why I have been talking about
this since 2017 name me a class 3 city that has any teeth show me the point is
that I answered the exam question but what I'm asking in response is for written stuff the public can read on their own time so we can get educated as well as y'all who are gonna be here next year so actually what I would recommend recommend instead of January, and I'm asking this of you specifically, counselor or med, I'd love it if that in February of next year, after you've returned to council, you request this conversation be brought to the public safety subcommittee with some of this documentation. Not because, yeah, this thing was so flawed. Clearly, it was flawed from the beginning when I put it together, because I was of the perspective based off someone up here on the dais that advisory would be fine. But then it got met with a bunch of hurdles. What we as the public need to help you move forward is information so i guess i'm asking you are you willing to get some of this information prepared over the next five months for us not all at once but just are you willing to work towards this and revisit this issue again in february once all the budget stuff
has died down and everything new is in place i mean i'll answer your question mr dastra and uh as been stated by other members of council and other members of the community we are all engaged in continuing conversations and and increasing relationships between the community and the police now what that looks like with the new council with the new administration with the new chair of the public safety committee and the new council i think that we should give those opportunities to actualize first and then we could continue to have those conversations as we are continuing to go on but as you stated you wrote this it was flawed as uh elected official i do not feel it's appropriate to move forward with it at this time but no one ever said that that that is going to cease conversations which we always strive to have with community members
sure so what i didn't ask you was to move this forward in february what i asked you is are you willing to get some written material put together for the public to understand what we have to do
to put teeth in this as a third class city mr dasher as we've stated before we are all in we're all engaged and committed to continue to do the work that we're elected to do and that is going GOING TO BE MY FINAL QUESTIONS, MY FINAL REMARKS ON THAT.
I FEEL LIKE IT'S THE SENATE RIGHT NOW.
THIS IS STILL YOUR COMMITTEE. I HAVE LOST TRACK OF WHETHER WE HAVE A MOTION AT THIS POINT. JUST A REMINDER.
I THINK IT DID. DIDN'T IT? I WASN'T SURE. I WILL MAKE A CLEAR MOTION TO
TABLE THIS. THANK YOU, SIR. UNTIL WHEN? INDEFINITELY. the conversation we cannot have a conversation about this until a police chief has been named at the minimum like it this is this is getting ridiculous table it and we'll have the conversation
at a more appropriate time mr harris do we have to have we need a specific date for tabling is that correct we do not no we do not great thank you okay is somebody gonna i'll move forward
and definitely is there anyone else is ahmed gonna agree to that well if there was a motion
in a second it would go to a vote of the committee all in favor was there a second was there a second
he was he seconded you i mean there was a motion in a second okay yeah i did not i did not second
i thought you seconded counselor diaz so i was waiting for the vote to come if there's a motion
without a second the motion fails i seconded i made the motion he seconded hirsch mr harris can you help as the parliamentarian
madam president my understanding is that mr hirsch made the motion uh the question is still uh before you for a second if councillor diaz is seconding the amendment then there can be a vote for
it is there a second to councillor hirsch's motion i seconded it i think you'll call the vote this is this is your committee so you may call a vote all in favor aye aye and that concludes the safety committee thank you we'll move to the committee of the whole and i will endeavor to be brief because of the late hour this evening we do have two items on our committee of the whole agenda versus bill number nine twenty twenty five this is a bill reallocating american rescue plan act funds that were granted to the lancaster recreation commission uh for a different use than what it was intended i don't know if we have anyone that's speaking to it director campbell i appreciate that i'd be happy to take a stab at it but i welcome you up thank you
so thank you very much this is an opportunity for us to make sure that arpa funds that were designated for one purpose can be continue to be used for a very similar in in line purpose um so the change in use for the arpa plant for the arpa funds is granted to the lancaster recreation commission for renovation of the price elementary school we are wanting since since lancaster rec has determined that they're not going to go forward with with price we want to be able to spend the remainder of the arpa dollars on other aspects of the renovation of the length existing lancaster facility which include hvac refurbishment of the elevator and refurbishment of the of the the structural bridge that the entrance bridge if there are sufficient funds the funds that had been allocated to from arpa were 750 000 uh we believe that there's about three hundred and seven thousand dollars left however both uh lancaster rec and sdol are confirming what has and has not been spent on the price building for not only asbestos abatement but for structural purposes we have reasonable estimates that the hvac which which dpw in the city of lancaster have been hobbling along with for the past two or three years with just window units can be performed for for under three hundred thousand dollars so if there is remaining three hundred seven thousand dollars and in then we can get the hvac done to everyone's satisfaction if we get better bids then we can go into the into the elevator which is a which we're estimating to be about 95 to 150 000 to do the elevator um and that's because the elevator has is several years beyond its remaining useful life and as a facility that is used by these seniors as well as a wide variety of individuals having handicapped accessibility throughout the facility would be very, very important. If we can only use the 307,000, if there's only 307,000 left, that's wonderful as far as we're concerned and we will continue through the facility condition assessment process to identify capital projects that can support the lancaster rec facility itself so the the goal here is to be able to legally allow i mean the the money section 804 of the third class city code says that money may not be paid out of the city treasury except by an appropriation made in accordance with the law and council may by ordinance make supplemental appropriation for any lawful purpose for any money in the city treasury so what we're asking is for the council to make that lawful supplemental appropriation thank you very much
director campbell um being well acquainted with the needs of that building i appreciate that we were going to be able to to move those funds into this purpose since the original one is is not able to move forward um question for you um just a procedural question are we uh are you asking for us to move this to our meeting on the 14th to expedite this process yes we are great um and
part of that is part of that is not just because of being expeditious but arpa funds need to be spent by the end of 2026 and we have the means to be able to spend these dollars within that TIME FRAME VERY VERY COMFORTABLY WITHOUT DELAY AND AS IT IS THE HVAC IS SOMETHING THAT COULD BENEFIT THE USE OF THE FACILITY NOT ONLY IN THE NOT ONLY IN THE SUMMERTIME FOR COOLING BUT IN
THE WINTERTIME FOR HEATING YES AND DESPERATELY NEEDED IN BOTH CASES THANK YOU ANY COMMENTS FROM COUNCIL ON THE BILL FROM THE PUBLIC HERE NONE I'LL MAKE A MOTION TO MOVE THIS TO OUR meeting on october 14th second all in favor aye aye any opposed thank you director campbell uh last item on our agenda this evening is our resolution number 64 2025 recognizing employee ownership month this is originated from council arroyo thank you council president um october is
employee ownership month so this resolution celebrates businesses where employees aren't just team members, but they're actually owners of the business. Employee-owned businesses thrive on shared success where every voice matters and also their contributions counts for everyone. You may recognize a nationally known employee-owned business that's right here in our city, which is Cargis. The founder and former CEO, Chip Cargis, started Tandem Center for Shared Business Success, which is a nonprofit based here in Lancaster that helps guide companies, not just in lancaster but across the nation become employee owned and it's just one example on how lancaster is being a leader in the business for good movement this resolution recognizes this recognizes october as employee ownership month and celebrates that success thank you very much
council royal any council comments on the resolution oh and i apologize i didn't make a motion before i did that um i would make a motion to move resolution number 64 2025 to council on the 14th second thank you any council comments on the resolution just procedural uh comments from the public on the resolution hearing none all in favor aye aye any opposed all right very good um we have received the clerk's report in writing before this meeting uh mr harris thank you very much for that um and having reached the conclusion of our agenda here motion to adjourn motion to adjourn oh don't all jump at once a second second All in favor? Aye. We're adjourned. Thank you.